<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of patience. Written by Father Francis Arias, of the Society of Iesus, in his second part of the Imitatio[n] of Christ our Lord. Translated into English</title>
            <author>Arias, Francisco.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 197 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 119 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115340</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850559</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850559</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15770</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21061)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15770)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 908:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of patience. Written by Father Francis Arias, of the Society of Iesus, in his second part of the Imitatio[n] of Christ our Lord. Translated into English</title>
                  <author>Arias, Francisco.</author>
                  <author>Tobie, Matthew, Sir, 1577-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 225, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Widow of C. Boscard],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>With permission of superiours, Anno 1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>A translation, by Sir Tobie Matthew, of the original by Francisco Arias.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Patience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15770:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15770:1"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF PATIENCE.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN BY FATHER FRANCIS ARIAS, OF THE Society of Ieſus, in his ſecond parte of the Imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated into Engliſh.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>In patientiâ vestrâ poſsidebitis ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas veſtras.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>In your <hi>Patience</hi> you ſhall poſſeſſe your ſoules.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>christogram</figDesc>
               <head>IHS</head>
            </figure>
            <p>With permiſſion of Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, Anno 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15770:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15770:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DICATORY. <hi>To the right honorable and moſt noble Lady, the Lady B. A.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAM</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>In the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Patience,</hi> I haue had no cauſe to exerciſe <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> for I diſpatched it
<pb facs="tcp:15770:3"/>with a great deale of guſt, in regard that I was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded therein by your Ladyship; the expreſsion of whoſe will giues euer occaſion of much ioy to mee. Now therefore, ſince, vpon the matter, it came from your Ladyship, it is but reaſon that it returne againe; though it muſt not be without the intereſt of my humbleſt thankes for your miniſtring mee ſo faire an occaſion, whereby I may haue ſeen more<pb facs="tcp:15770:3"/>clearly what in my ſelfe I ought to be; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently what I am not: To the end that hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if I growe not more patient, yet at leaſt I may grow more hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble, through the too certaine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of my great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.</p>
            <p>Your Ladyship, I aſſure my ſelfe, will be pleaſed to looke vpon it with at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention; eſpecially in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of what it is in it ſelfe; though partly alſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe<pb facs="tcp:15770:4"/>it is a poore preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of mine And I shall pray our good God, with whole my heart, that you alſo may be much the better by it, in thanking his diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, for that which you shall perceiue him to haue giuen you, and in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him hard, to enrich you, with whatſoeuer you may yet finde your ſelfe in this vertue to want. And if his holy name may be glorified hereby, and your ſoule and mine aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted
<pb facs="tcp:15770:4"/>to doe him the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeruice, it is that very reward, which moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly I would beſtowe vpon my ſelfe for this little labour, though I had all power in mine owne ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds: yours Ladyships, I moſt humblie kiſſe, and doe you reuerence, with the hart of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A moſt obliged and moſt humble ſeruant euer. T. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:15770:5"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF THE CHAPTERS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE I. CHAPTER. <hi>IN what the vertue of</hi> Patience
<hi>conſiſts; and how the ſupernaturall fauours of God are neceſſary for our ſuffering the miſeries of this life with true Patience</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 2. <hi>Of the euils, or inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences of paine which Chriſt our Lord beganne to ſuffer euen from his Conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, and Birth; and of the example of Patience, which he gaue vs therein.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 3. <hi>How Christ our Lord en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured the company of the wicked, and of the example of Patience, which he gaue vs thereby.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 4. <hi>Of the euills of paine, which Chriſt our Lord ſuffered in his Paſsion; and of the example of Patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which he gaue vs, by ſuffering them with ſo great good will</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 5. <hi>Of the Patience, deſire,<pb facs="tcp:15770:5"/>and loue, wherwith Christ our Lord indured all thoſe torments, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and edification of our ſoules.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 6. <hi>Of the Patience wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wee ought to ſuffer the loſſe of temporall goods, and of the example which Christ our Lord gaue vs herein.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 7. <hi>Of the Patience, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wee are to endure corporall infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; and of the example, which Chriſt our Lord hath giuen vs herein.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 8. <hi>Of the other great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, which are drawen from corporall infirmities, when they are borne with Patience.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 9. <hi>Wherein it is confirmed, by the example of Saints, how great the fruite of ſicknes, and other tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is; and how this is an effect of Gods mercy, which he shewes towards his friends.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 10. <hi>Of the fruite of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Faith, and Patience, which wee muſt gather from the Patience,<pb facs="tcp:15770:6"/>which the Saints haue shewed in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their infirmities and paines.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 11. <hi>Of the Patience wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with diſcomforts, and ſpirituall deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, are to be endured; and of the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which Chriſt our Lord gaue hereof.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 12. <hi>Of the neceſsity, and fruite of Patience; and how it is a ſigne of the election and predeſtination of God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 13. <hi>How pleaſing the vertue of Patience is to God, and of the great fauours which he affoardes them, who ſuffer with Patience.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 14. <hi>Of the meanes, whereby the vertue of Patience may be obtained; which is, that wee be watchfull to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the fruite thereof, and the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples whereby wee haue been taught it by Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 15. <hi>Of other meanes wherby wee are to obtaine, and conſerue the vertue of Patience, namely to conſider our ſinnes, and to reſort to Almighty God, for the remedy thereof.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:15770:6"/>
            <head>A prayer for obteining Patience of Almighty God.</head>
            <p>WHy doe I complaine, ô Lord, when I am wronged, or affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vniuſtly; if I call to minde how grieuouſly I haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded thee; how often I haue deſerued Hell; how great thy mercy is, appointing me to ſuffer light temporall puniſhment in this life, wheras I haue deſerued moſt grieuous and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting torments, in the next? For it is not fitting that there ſhould be delicate mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers vnder a thorny head, and which hath been moſt cruelly vſed for them. Why ſhould I complaine, if I doe but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that for ſuffering patiently for a time theſe preſent labours, thy mercy will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me, and with thine owne hand thou wilt wipe the teares from mine eyes, and wilt giue reſt to my broken and afflicted bones; and that thy comfort and reward will be according to the meaſure of my
<hi>Patience</hi> and ſuffering. Let therefore whatſoeuer aduerſities reine downe vpon me for thy ſake, ô Lord; ſo that thou giue me ſtrength and ſpirit to endure them: becauſe that, without the helpe of thy grace, the weakenes of my nature would<pb facs="tcp:15770:7"/>faile. Make me, ô Lord, to beare all falſe iudgements, vaine ſuſpicious, ſlaunders, al iniuries couragiouſly, without repining, without complaining, without excuſes, without any interiour feeling of them, and without any exteriour ſigne: and let my ſoule be ſo much the more ioyed and delighted within it ſelfe; by how much the more innocent it findeth it ſelfe, and free from the fault, where with it is char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Strengthen my ſoule, ô Lord, with the knowledge and loue of thy moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Paſſion, that I may not only beare preſent aduerſities with ioy, but alſo wiſh them when they are abſent: and that I may account it a kinde of croſſe, to liue and dy without a croſſe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15770:7"/>A SHORT TREATISE OF PATIENCE VVRITTEN BY Father Francis Arrias in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d part of his booke of the imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt our Lord.</head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>THE I. CHAPTER. <hi>In What the vertue of Patience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts; and how the ſupernaturall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of God are neceſſary for our ſuffering the miſeries of this life with true Patience.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T belongs to the vertue of true <hi>Patience,</hi> to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer all thoſe thinges, which are aduerſe, and ſerue for <pb n="2" facs="tcp:15770:8"/>the puniſhment of man in this mortal life, with a heart ſo firm, and conſtant, that to auoyd and fly from them, he doe nothing which is faulty, and contrary to the will of Almighty God. It belongs alſo to
<hi>Patience,</hi> that the ſorrow which naturally is raiſed in the ſoule of man, by the approach and preſence of miſeries, be moderated and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued in ſuch ſorte, as that it may doe no harme to the ſame ſoule, by putting it into diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and by making it ſwarue from the right line of reaſon. This is that <hi>Patience</hi> which is neceſſary for vs, and to which wee are bound by expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment; whereby a man is ſecured from co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting either mortall or veniall ſinne in ſuch occaſions. But other degrees of <hi>Patience</hi> there are of greater per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15770:8"/>which belong to Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, and not to commaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereof wee ſhall ſpeake afterward.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes this
<hi>Patience,</hi> which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for vs, after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.
<hi>Patience</hi> conſiſts in ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe euills of puniſhment, which happen to vs by the will of others, with a moderate and equall minde; and in that a man diſpoſe not himſelf to hurt that other ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, from whom it comes; and that receiuing the ſcourges of paine and ſorrow, and other tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s at the hand of God, he complaine not, &amp; murmure not againſt him. And declaring elswhere, how it is not neceſſary for this
<hi>Patience,</hi> to which wee are bound by precept, to quench intirely that ſorrow and grief, which a mind receiues through<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15770:9"/>the euills of puniſhment, but to moderate it in ſuch ſorte, as that it may not be inordinate and hurtfull, he ſaith thus; Some thinke that true conſtancy and wiſdome, conſiſts in not feeling thoſe ſcourges, and contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, which come to vs in this life from the hand of God; and others haue too exceſſiue ſence thereof, and are too much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and diſmaied therby; but the true vertue of <hi>Patience,</hi> and true wiſdome teaches vs to hold the meane between thoſe two Extremes. In ſuch ſorte, as that a Chriſtian muſt neither be of a ſtupid heart (becauſe this neceſſary vertue of <hi>Patience</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts not, in that a man feele no ſorrow for his aduerſity) nor yet that on the other ſide he ſhould feele ſo much diſmay &amp; griefe as to make him paſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15770:9"/>the bounds of reaſon. For if he exceed therein, he offends againſt the vertue of <hi>Patience.</hi> And becauſe it happenes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that ſome, when a croſſe arriues, or when a wrong is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, doe by the helpe of God beare it well at that time; and yet remembring it afterward, fall either into ſorrow, or into rage, with impatience againſt him who offended them, the ſame Saint pronounces thus. He is the poſſeſſor of true
<hi>Patience,</hi> who at the time when he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues the hurt, doth beare it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inordinate grief; and when afterward he happenes to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber it, reioyces and is glad that he e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dured it. And the end which a faithfull Chriſtian is to hould, in the ſuffera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of theſe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and in vſing this mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and in putting this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15770:10"/>vpon griefe, muſt be to conforme himſelfe to the good pleaſure of God; and to will that, which God wills. For the will of God is, that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould vnder goe that euill of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by whatſoeuer way it come to him; whether it be by meanes of diuells, or men, or other creatures. For by whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer meanes it comes, God is the firſt Author, &amp; the firſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe from whence it proceeds; and ſo his pleaſure is, that men ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, and accept well thereof, as growinge to them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his hand. This is Saint <hi>Paules</hi> aduice, <hi>Heb. 10.</hi> when he ſpeakes thus to his faithfull children. Becauſe you are encountred with ſo many croſſes, which aſſault the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of your hearts, you haue need of
<hi>Patience,</hi> whereby you may in all thinges, performe the will of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15770:10"/>God, and yeeld entire obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to his comaundments. And complying after this manner with his heauenly will, you ſhall obtaine thoſe moſt high and eternall benedictions, which the Diuine Maieſtie hath promiſed to ſuch as keepe his lawe.</p>
            <p>Now by reaſon that mans weaknes, after the fall of Adam, is ſo great, it is a matter of much difficulty for him to ſuffer all thoſe euils of puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which happen to him in this life, with ſuch ſtrength of minde, as that he tranſgreſſe not the bounds of reaſon, and the lawe of God. And if wee conſider man in his naturall force, not onely is this hard for him, but wholly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. For though as Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaith well, a man, for the enioying of temporall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, endure eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15770:11"/>of nature many grieuous thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, becauſe the naturall loue, which he carries to himſelf, hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes him on; and with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter naturall loue, he ouer comes another loue which is leſſe; yet to obtaine ſpirituall and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall bleſſings, wherein conſiſts our ſaluation, which is the true end of vertue, he is not able to endure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For a naturall loue, is not able to produce this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: but a loue ſupernaturall, and grace from heauen is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the enduring thereof. And ſo wee ſee, that the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers and wiſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world, who by the ſtrayning vpon the force of nature, did profeſſe to obtaine the true vertue of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> were able indeed to reach but to the ſhadow and appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thereof, as Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> notes in theſe wordes. I finde not, O<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15770:11"/>my brethren, that amongſt all the wayes of ſpirit which are taught vs by our holy Religion, any one of them is more vſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, towards the obtayning of the Kingdome of heauen, then this of perfect <hi>Patience.</hi> This was profeſſed by the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers; but as the wiſdome which they profeſſed was for the moſt part not ſollid, and true; ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was their <hi>Patience;</hi> becauſe no man can be truly wiſe, or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, who knowes not the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and <hi>Patience</hi> of God by way of faith. This is the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of S. <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therfore, ſince the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of man is ſo great, in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring croſſes with <hi>Patience,</hi> and that he is in ſo great neceſſity thereof, for liuing well in this world, and for the obreyning of heauen in the next; it pleaſed<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15770:12"/>Chriſt our Lord, to prouide vs with two very principall and efficacious remedies, for the ſtrengthening of our weakenes, and for the exalting of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; in ſuch ſorte, as that it might obtayne this diuine ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and the perfection thereof, with much facility. One of theſe meanes, is the example of his moſt holy life, &amp; paſſion, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may be animated to beare croſſes with <hi>Patience;</hi> and the other are thoſe ſupernaturall helpes, and ſuccours of grace, which he deſerued for vs, by his ſufferings. Let vs therefore goe declaring the chief examples of his life, whereby he moues, and perſwades vs, to ſuffer all the aduerſities, paines, torments &amp; contradictions which may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to vs in this world, with true <hi>Patience.</hi> To the end that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15770:12"/>them at good leaſure, and with true feeling and ſpirit, wee may ſtirre our ſelues vp to an effectuall purpoſe, and deſire to beare Croſſes. And ſo alſo, by a liuely faith of thoſe ſo holy and bleſſed Myſteries, &amp; by the the meanes of humble and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uont prayer, we ſhall obtaine all thoſe ſuccours of grace, which are needfull for the bearing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with perfect <hi>Patience.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>THE II. CHAPTER. <hi>Of the euils or inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniences of payne which Chriſt our Lord beganne to ſuffer euen from his Conception, and Birth; and of the example of Patience, which he gaue vs therein.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe ſonne of God, as ſoon as he was borne into the world, did inſtantly ſuffer paine<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15770:13"/>and ſorrow. He inſtantly felt the paine of cold, for he was born in winter, and in an open vndefended place. And for as much as the body of the infant <hi>Ieſus,</hi> was extreamely tender, &amp; delicate, in regard that he was of a moſt perfect pure comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion, he felt the iniuries and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities of the ſeaſon, more then euer any other infant did, how delicate ſoeuer he might be. Vpon the arriuall of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth day, he felt the grief and torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Circumciſion, which was extreame. For if they, who were growen men, did feele it much, becauſe the paine in it ſelfe was great, as alſo for that they had reaſon wherewith to vnderſtand it; how much more muſt the infant
<hi>Ieſus</hi> feele that paine; who, with being of ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate conſtitution, had alſo the<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15770:13"/>vſe of reaſon in perfection. And this paine of his was increaſed in him, becauſe the Virgin, who was preſent there, and ſawe the blood and teares which the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant ſhed, did all melt with grief; and, hauing her heart full of a moſt dolorous compaſſion, would be ſure to ſigh, and ſhed mournfull teares. And her moſt bleſſed ſonne, obſeruing the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of his moſt ſacred mother, whom he incomparably loued, and of whoſe ſorrow he well knew how great it was, had much pitty of her; and that pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cauſed a greater wound of ſorrow in his ſoule, then the knife had made in his body.</p>
            <p>This ſorrow for the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, was followed, at the end of little more then thirty daies, by his baniſhment, into Aegypt; whither the way was very long,<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15770:14"/>and very painfull: and tooke vp the toyle of many dayes, and the baniſhment laſted many yeares.</p>
            <p>Another immenſe ſorrow,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich Chriſt our Lord endured, and which began in him from the inſtant of his Conception, and continued till his expiring vpon the Croſſe, was that which was cauſed in him, by all the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the whole world, for they al were prese<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to him; both thoſe which had bene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted from the beginning of the world till that time, and thoſe which then were in committing; and thoſe alſo which would be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted euentill the very end of the world. Now the man who loues God and his neighbours in great meaſure, is much afflicted by offences committed againſt God, and by the loſſe of ſoules:<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15770:14"/>and ſo much more as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loues God, and his neighbours, ſo much more is the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, and the loſſe of ſoules, intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to him. So ſaith Saint
<hi>Peter.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>ep.</hi> 2.
<hi>c.</hi> that the ſinnes of the Inhabitants of Sodom, did grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the ſoule of holy Lot, day and night. Since ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt our Lord, did ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premely loue the glory of the eternall Father, and the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſoules; he hauing all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes preſent to him, ſo many ſinnes, whereby the eternall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was affronted, and ſoules deſtroyed and condemned; that moſt ſacred ſoule became a very ſea of immenſe ſorrowe, which tormented it euer day &amp; night without either ceſſation, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
            <p>Another moſt greiuous tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which Chriſt our Lord was
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15770:15"/>pleaſed to ſuffer for vs, was to be tempted by the diuell in the deſart. For to be tempted, is to be prouoked, and ſolicited to ſin; which is a thing moſt vgly and to be abhorred. And this was not onely a vaſt affront to him, by meanes whereof he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed Humility (as we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared elswhere;) but it was alſo an exceſſiue grief to him, by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion whereof he exerciſed <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</hi> For if ſome moſt chaſt virgin who were a great louer of purity, and a great deteſter of all diſhoneſty, being ſeen alone by ſome filthy perſon, &amp; being ſolicited by his ſpeech to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit vncleannes, would feele more offence, and paine therby, then if they ſhould beate her with cudgells, or dragg her by the haire, through the ſtreetes; much more would Chriſt our
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15770:15"/>Lord, who did ſupremely loue the will, and glory of his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Father, and who deeply de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted all kinde of ſinne, finde it for an incomparable kinde of torment, and feele it more then many of the torments of his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Paſſion, to ſee himſelf ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and prouoked by the diuell, to affront his Father, and to commit ſo wicked, and ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable a thing, as ſinne is.</p>
            <p>This torment was accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed by another, which was to be carryed by the diuell from the deſart to the pinacle of the Temple; and from thence to the top of the mountaine. Which, whether it were, that he were taken vp, &amp; carryed in the ayre, as ſome of the Saints vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it: or that the diuel guided him, like one who would lead an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other by the hand, as other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15770:16"/>writers haue conceaued, the diuell being ſo wicked, and ſo deformed a creature, and Chriſt our Lord ſeeing ſo cleerly that malice and deformity of his, and yet to be ſo long ſo neer him, and to be touched or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed by him, muſt needes be of ſo exceſſiue paine to him, as to equall many torments of his Paſſion. And ſo doth Saint
<hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> compare it ſaying; when wee heare them tell, that Chriſt our Lord, being true God and man, was carryed by the diuell to the Citty of Ieruſalem, it cauſeth horrour and amazeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in ſuch as heare it. But yet it is no wonder, that he ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer himſelfe to be carryed by the deuill, who is the head of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes; ſince he was pleaſed to be crucified by the members of the ſame diuel. This is the ſaying<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15770:16"/>of S. <hi>Gregory;</hi> whereby he ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifies, that the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to haue bene carryed by that infernall beaſt the diuell, imports a kind of a reſemblance to that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther torment, of his hauing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne crucified by ſinners; and ſo doubtles it was a moſt greiuous affliction to the ſoule of Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <p>All thoſe croſſes and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, which Chriſt our Lord ſuffered, through the whole courſe of his preaching; the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury of ill wordes; the deeds of perſecution which were caſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him; the ſlaunders, falſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, the attempt to breake his necke downe the hill in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth, and to ſtone him many times in Ieruſalem, belong to the vertue of Humility, in as much as they carryed diſgrace and contempt with them; but
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15770:17"/>for him to haue made choice, and to haue imbraced them, in regard that they were painfull, and dolorous to his heart; and to indure them as ſuch, belonges to the vertue of <hi>Patience.</hi> And Chriſt our Lord indured them with ſo extreeme <hi>Patience,</hi> that whereas he might moſt iuſtly haue taken ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geance of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, for euery one of thoſe pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in particuler; and might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly haue deliuered them ouer to the furie of hell, there to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that torment, which they deſerued; or els might haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilated them, by taking off his hand of protection and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation from them; yet he would not doe them any hurt at all, not gaue he to them by way of anſwere, any word, which might be ſo ſeuere or ſharpe, as might occaſion the leaſt diſguſt <pb n="21" facs="tcp:15770:17"/>to them; but he conſerued them in being and life, and he gaue them holy inſpirations; and all the actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which he performed, and all the wordes, which he vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, were ordayned to make them doe penance, &amp; that they might not be loſt and damned, but become ſaued ſoules in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p>At that time did he endure the ſociety, and the ſinnes of that miſerable Iudas, with vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Patience.</hi> Our Lord percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued well, the malice and ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of his hart; the thefts which he committed vpon the almes, which was deliuered to his care; &amp; that trechery, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he knew he would ſell him ouer to his enemies; and yet did he not caſt him out of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, nor did he depriue him of the dignity and authority of his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15770:18"/>Apoſtolate, wherof he had made himſelfe ſo vnworthy; nor ſpake he any word of affront to him, nor ſhewed him any offended or vntoward countenance, but he affoarded him al thoſe common benefits and fauours, which be imparted to the reſt of his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>By theſe examples of <hi>Patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,</hi> which our Lord gaue vs in the time of his life, and courſe of his preaching, he taught and perſwaded vs to haue <hi>Patience;</hi> whereby wee are to ſuffer all the croſſes and contradictions of this life; and all the perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, oppreſſions, and iniuries of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; not giuing place, nor ſo much as entry into our harts, to ill will, or hatred againſt any man; nor for complaints or murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring either againſt God, or ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; nor yet to any inordinate grief:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15770:18"/>but ſuffering them with a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, firme &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant minde, which ſwarues not from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitude and rule of vertue; and is deſirous, that in all thinges the will of God may be fulfilled. So ſaith Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently deſcribing the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the <hi>Patience</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, by theſe wordes.</p>
            <p>What glory is ſo great, as that a man may become like God, in the exerciſe of <hi>Patience,</hi> endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the inconueniences of this life, and the iniuries of men, as God doth long endure the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences which ſinners commit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. Which <hi>Patience, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus-Christ</hi> our Lord did teach vs, as he was man; not onely by word, but by deed alſo. For he ſaid, he came into the world to worke the will of his father. And amongſt thoſe other admirable<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15770:19"/>vertues, whereby he diſcouered to vs the power of his diuinity; one was, the <hi>Patience</hi> whereby he imitated his eternall Father; and ſo all thoſe thinges which he did, from the time when he was borne with mortall fleſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this world, did carry the ſeale and ſtampe of <hi>Patience</hi> vpon them. For he tooke on him, as hath been ſaid, the waight of all the ſinnes of men, that he might pay by ſuffering for them. He was tempted by the enemy; and yet he did him noe hurt for it: but was onely content to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him. He endured the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible wickednes of Iudas, with a <hi>Patience</hi> ſo large, as laſted till the end of his life. He endured the Iewes who were incredulous, vngratefull, proud, rebellious, and contrary both to his doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and to his example. And he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15770:19"/>indured them in ſuch ſorte, as to heape benefits vpon them; and to treate them with meekenes, and to receiue ſuch of them to his fauour and friendſhip, as would be conuerted to him. What grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<hi>Patience,</hi> and what greater clemency can be conceiued, then by meanes of ſhedding his blood to purchaſe, and to impart a life of grace and glory to them, who through hatred, and by moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked meanes, tooke a courſe to ſpill that very blood? And ſince wee are the members and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt our Lord, who is the way of ſaluation and life it ſelfe, it will become vs to follow his example. Theſe ar the wordes of Saint
<hi>Cyprian.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:15770:20"/>
            <head>THE III. CHAPTER. <hi>How Christ our Lord endured the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the wicked, and of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Patience, which he gaue vs thereby.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ONe of the thinges which good men finde moſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to endure, in this life, is the ſociety and conuerſation of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, whileſt they continue in their wickednes. For in regard that they abhorre ſinne ſo much, and haue ſuch feeling of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, which are committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and of the loſſe and damnation of ſoules; for them to ſee thoſe offences before their eyes, and to obſerue their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to lie vnder the wrath of God, condemned and loſt, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſtate of preſent iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15770:20"/>&amp; yet not feeling their own miſery, by reaſon of the great blindenes and obſtinacy, wherein they are; and to ſee withall, that they can prouide no remedy for this ſo great miſchiefe, nor giue any impediment to theſe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt God, and to this loſſe of ſoules; they receiue, I ſay, her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by intollerable paine; and carry their hearts euen tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſperſed from ſide to ſide with the ſword of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; and haue extreame deſires to depart out of the ſociety &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of ſuch ſinners, and to be ſtill remayning farr from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And in regard this miſery hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens ſometimes to good men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſometimes the wicked are ſuch perſons, as whoſe company they cannot leaue, becauſe they are either ſonnes, or parents, or brothers, or husband, or wife, or their gouernours, or ſeruaunts of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15770:21"/>the ſame Lord, or ſubiects of the ſame Prelate, their paine &amp; grief doth extreamly increaſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this occaſion. Now how veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t this torment is, for good men to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure; and how great deſire they haue, for as much as may concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne themſelues, to depart out of their company, Chriſt our Lord himſelf, did o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce declare in waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie wordes.
<hi>Matt.</hi> 17. <hi>Marc</hi> 9. When he deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded from the Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, he came to thoſe troopes of people, which were expecting him, and he found his diſciples much afflicted and confounded, in that men had brought one to them, who was both a poſſeſſed &amp; a lunaticke perſon, whom they were not able to cure. And by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion thereof the Scribes and Phariſees, who were preſent, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached them, as wanting ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue from heauen to ſend deuills<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15770:21"/>out, and they affirmed that their Maſter did it in the power of Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebub. Saint Marke ſignifies thus much, by ſaying that Chriſt our Lord fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the Scribes in debate, and argument with his diſciples. And then our Lord ſaid to them; O you incredulous and rebellious generation, how long ſhall I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, &amp; conuerſe amongſt you, how long ſhall I expect you, and endure your obſtinacy &amp; malice. By theſe wordes did Chriſt our Lord declare the trouble which the wickednes and conuerſation with vitious perſons, who would not be conuerted and hindered the conuerſion of others, did put him to, and that he felt that paine more then death it ſelfe. So ſaith Saint <hi>Chriſoſtome.</hi> Our Lord ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by this, that he euen deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red death, and that his Paſſion was not to be troubleſom, or grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15770:22"/>to him; but that the thing whereof he was moſt ſenſible, and which afflicted him moſt, was to conuerſe with rebellious ſinners, who made reſiſtance to the truth; and vpon whom he ſawe, that the fruite both of his life, and death would be loſt.</p>
            <p>Now as this was an immenſe torment to Chriſt our Lord, ſo is it very grieuous to be endured by vertuous men. But that which they are to doe, for ſuffering it with that <hi>Patience</hi> which is fit, and for gathering from thence, that fruite of merits which God deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, is this: To diſtinguiſh on the one ſide, by the vſe of reaſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween that which is the fault of others, and the loſſe of ſoules, and the offence of God; and that on the other ſide, which is their owne affliction, and paine; and then to be afflicted for thoſe ſinnes, for<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15770:22"/>aſmuch as they imply the offence of God, and withal to be ſory for the loſſe, which ſoules receiue thereby, and to make inſtant prayer to God for them; and as for the paine and torment, which reſults thereby vpon them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, to accept it at the hands of almighty God, and willingly, to be content to ſuffer it, during all that time, which God ſhal thinke fit not to take them out of that company, and conuerſation of the wicked. By this meanes, that company of the wicked, will be a diuine Purgatory to them; which may cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe their ſoules both from ſinnes, and the puniſhments due thereunto; and a way of exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing chatity and humility, and patience, which ar of ſo great worth and merit, and ſo very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>And to animate them to ſuffer<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15770:23"/>this puniſhment with this <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> they are to conſider thoſe exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of Chriſt our Lord, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee haue ſpoken; which are, the immenſe and continuall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which he felt in behoulding all the ſinnes of mankinde; and that which he felt in being car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed by the diuell to Ieruſalem, and to the Mount; &amp; that which he receiued by his conuerſation with the Iewes, who continued rebellious in their infidelity; and that particularly, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by keeping Iudas in his company, and in the Colledge of his Apoſtles. For to this end it was, that he choſe that miſerable creature for an Apoſtle; as well knowing how wicked he was to be; and for this, after he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, did he continue him in his owne company; and he tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated him, to the end that by<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15770:23"/>this example they might ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie endeauour to endure thoſe wicked and peruerſe people with
<hi>Patience,</hi> whom they might chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to haue in their neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, their houſe, their family and their ſociety. So doth Saint
<hi>Augustine</hi> aduiſe vs ſaying. Chriſt our Lord had one amongſt his Apoſtles, who was wicked; and he ſerued himſelfe well of that wickednes. Firſt, by complying with that eternall ordination of God concerning his Paſſion; and ſecondly to giue an example to the world, of the <hi>Patience</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were to endure wicked men.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore animate our felues, by theſe exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of Chriſt our God and Sauiour, to ſuffer with a good will, and a conſtant minde, whatſoeuer troubles, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, and croſſes may grow
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15770:24"/>to vs, by our neighbours, our domeſticks, and our familiar freinds. Let vs conſider and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der well, what Chriſt our Lord endured at the hands of ſinners, for the loue of vs; and how he hath endured our very ſelues, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling our ſinnes, when we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued hell for committing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; beſtowing benefits on vs, when wee committed offences againſt him; imparting mercies to vs, when wee did him wronges; cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge out, and drawing vs to him, and conuerting vs by his grace, when we had departed from him, and were fled out of his houſe, and were making warre againſt his Law. This <hi>Patience</hi> of Chriſt our Lord, wherwith as God he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures all ſinners, &amp; hath endured our ſelues; and, as man, endured thoſe wicked people with whom he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſt in this world, muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15770:24"/>and ſtrengthen vs much, in the way of ſufferance.</p>
            <p>Great (ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) is the <hi>Patience</hi> of God, in not inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie puniſhing ſinners, but in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering them for ſometime, till they may be conuerted. And in another place; If our Lord, our God, and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, who with one ſingle word could haue caſt his enemies into the moſt profound pit of hell, did yet endure them with
<hi>Patience,</hi> why ſhould not miſerable men, who are full of ſinnes endure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo with <hi>Patience,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this life they receiue paine and trouble from other men, by whoſe meanes they are corrected, and puniſhed by Almighty God for their ſinnes? This is the diſcourſe of Saint <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe.</hi> Let vs therefore giue this glory to God, that for his loue wee may endure all euills of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; <pb n="36" facs="tcp:15770:25"/>Let vs yeeld this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour a d giue this guſt to Chriſt our Sauiour, in that, to imitate him, wee may haue occaſion to ſuffer all the iniuries, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of men. Let vs beſtow this benefit vpon our owne ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les in wiping away our ſinnes by exerciſing this vertue of <hi>Patience;</hi> and let vs fill it full of comforts, and merits. For, as <hi>Eccleſiaſticus chap.</hi> 1. ſaith, <hi>the Patient man ſuffers onely during a time</hi> which is limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and afterward, for his hauing ſuffered, Almighty God giues him true ioy, which ſpringes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that grace which at the preſent he receiues, and from that hope of glory, wherewith he is to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed afterward.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:15770:25"/>
            <head>THE IV. CHAPTER. <hi>Of the euils of paine, which Chriſt our Lord ſuffered in his Paſsion; and of the example of Patience, which he gaue vs, by ſuffering them with ſo great good will.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe chief examples of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> which Chriſt our Lord gaue vs, were of his moſt ſacred Paſſion, by reaſon of the many, and various kindes of ſorrowes, and tormentes which he ſuffered therein, with vnſpeakeable <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience:</hi> and wee will declare theſe torments, and the <hi>Patience</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he ſuffered them; for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of our ſoules; and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly that wee may learne to ſuffer all the miſeries of this life with <hi>Patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When they apprehended our<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15770:26"/>Lord (he giuing them leaue to put the malice and fury of their wrathed harts in execution) the torments were many, and very grieuous which they gaue him, with their hands, and feet, by cudgells, and irons, and other inſtruments, which they had, and vſed throughout that whole way, till they came to the houſe of
<hi>Annas.</hi> For if, after they had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed vpon his perſon, ſo many and moſt cruell kindes of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, through all that night, and ſo much of the next day, till they nailed him faſt to the croſſe, they yet were not ſatiſfied at all; but after they had crucified him, they did yet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue to perſecute him, with their viperous tongues; and after they had fetched all the blood out of his vaines, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his life, they would nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des open his ſide, and fetch the<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15770:26"/>blood forth from his very heart; what is to be thought, that they would doe in that furious onſet, when firſt they began to exerciſe their cruelty vpon him, and to ſtreame out their deadly poiſon againſt him, which had lyen for ſo long time horded vp in their malitious heartes?</p>
            <p>In the houſe of <hi>Caiphas,</hi> the High Prieſt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt our Lord had confeſſed who he was, and when all the Iudges had condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him as a blaſphemous perso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and worthy death; the ſoldiers &amp; Miniſters of iuſtice, together with the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the Prieſts in whoſe power he was, ruſhed in vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him with extreame cruelty, and moſt grieuouſly tormented him, with buffers, blowes, and ſpitting on him; and they went continuing, and augmenting thoſe torments, throughout that whole night,<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15770:27"/>with many inuentions, all full of cruelty &amp; helliſh fury. And ſome holy men, to whom God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed many ſecrets of his life &amp; death, haue ſaid, that in that night, our moſt bleſſed Lord was ſtroken foure hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred times, with hard buffets, and cruell blowes, vpon his face and necke, and all the reſt of the parts of his moſt bleſſed body.</p>
            <p>This paſſed in the houſe of the High Prieſt; and now let vs ſee, what torments he ſuffered in the houſe of Pilate. The firſt was, to be bound to a pillar, and there to be moſt cruelly ſcourged. What extreame paine muſt it be, for him to be tyed ſo forcibly to a pillar, that the cordes and ropes would be e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tering ſo deep into his delicate fleſh, as to make the blood euen breake forth? What torment, nay what flood of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15770:27"/>would it be, for him to be ſcourged after that manner. For the whippes; wherewith they did it, were moſt cruell, conſiſting of ſharpe rods, and biting cords, which (as many affirme) had hookes and ſpurres of iron at the ends thereof. The executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners were ſtrong, fierce &amp; many; who yet changed by turnes; and all were full of mortall hate and ſpite againſt our Lord. His ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred fleſh was moſt tender, and moſt delicate, and all framed of the blood of that moſt pure Virgin. The imaginatiue parte of Chriſt our Lord did perceiue euerye one of thoſe ſcourges, which they gaue him, after a moſt diſtinct and perfect manner. In other men, the feeling of a dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per paine or grief doth aſtoniſh the imagination; &amp; ſo they haue no feeling of other leſſer paines:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15770:28"/>and therefore it happens, that ſome ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may haue his very skull parted, and his body thruſt through, and yet not feele the paine; by hauing his imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo much imployed, and diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by his inward Paſſion and rage. But in Chriſt our Lord it was not ſo: for he had his imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and the apprehenſion of his ſoule ſo perfectly bent vpon euery particular paine, which he felt, as if he had onely felt that ſingle paine; &amp; the ſence and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of one paine, did not hinder his feeling of any other. And this proceeded from the great perfection which he had in all the powers and ſences, both of his ſacred body, and ſoule. Thoſe ſcourges being ſo cruell, and thoſe executioners being ſo able and ſtrong, and his ſence of the paine ſo perfect, there was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15770:28"/>ſo great multitude of ſtrokes, and blowes, which he receiued, that ſome holy men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that thoſe which were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted vpon him at the pillar, did paſſe the number of fiue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand. And not onely did they ſcourge his backe, but after they had dreſt that in ſuch a faſhion, that there was nothing to be ſeen but wounds and blood, they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyed him firſt, and then tyed him againe, with his backe turned towards the pillar; and ſcourged him the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d time, with the ſame cruelty, vpon the belly, breſt, face, &amp; all the other parts, which were diſcouered; in ſuch ſorte, as that the whole moſt holy body of Chriſt our Lord, was flead, and plowed ouer, into ſuch furrowes, as diſcouered the very bones. And he who had bene the moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull of all thoſe men whom God
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15770:29"/>euer made, remained ſo disfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and deformed, that it was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen a horrour to behould him. So ſaith Saint <hi>Augustine.</hi> The force of thoſe cruell ſcourges being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed ſo many times, did breake the skin, and diſcouered the very fleſh of the moſt bleſſed body of Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <p>That torment of his ſcourging was followed by that other tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the crowne of thornes. For thoſe Pagan ſoldiers, to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe the chiefe of the Iewes, and (as Saint <hi>Chriſostome</hi> ſaith) for the intereſt of that money, which was giuen them to the end that they might be the more cruel towards him, tooke our Lord into their power, who was already woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and as it were euen all ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by thoſe ſcourges; and then they placed him all tremblinge with cold, in the Court of Pilates<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15770:29"/>houſe; and in that publike Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, in the ſight of all that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they ſtript him againe of his owne cloathes; and they put an old purple veſt vpon him for ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne; and vpon his head a crowne of thornes.</p>
            <p>This act of theirs, beſides that it was of extreame affront (as we haue already ſhewed,) was alſo moſt painful to him: for the thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whereof the crowne was wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, were extreame heard and ſharpe; and they enuironed his whole head, and temples; and they paſſed and penetrated them, euen to the veines, nerues and bones; &amp; made his ſacred blood, ſtreame downe ouer his face, his necke and his haire. The ſacred head of Chriſt our Lord had in all that day, &amp; the night before, receiued innumerable blowes, &amp; woundes; ſometimes with cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, <pb n="46" facs="tcp:15770:30"/>other times with irons, ſometimes with ſwordes, other ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes with gauntlets, and often with the fiſts; and by this meanes it was ſo battered, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer touched it, cauſed exceſſe of paine being then ſuch already, and then inſtantly placing a crowne of thornes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, ſo cruel as this, whereof wee haue ſpoken; what exceſſiue paine, or rather torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, would it be ſure to cauſe? And to this it may be added; that the paine and torment which the crowne of thornes cauſed; had no intermiſſion like thoſe others, which either were ſoone ended or much diminiſhed, but it ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, and laſted euen till his very death. For he euer had it on, and the thornes ſerued to nayle it to his head; and if at any time they tooke it off, either to cloath, or ſtrip him, they inſtantly put it
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15770:30"/>on againe. And not only did theſe ſorrowes laſt till his death, but they encreaſed much. For, euery time when they ſtroke his head, either with the cane, or any other inſtrument of paine; and euery time when the crowne did by chaunce ſtirre of it ſelfe, that paine renewed, and encreaſed.</p>
            <p>Another principall torment, which followed vpon this, was to lay the Croſſe vpon his backe, that ſo he might carry it to the place, where he was to be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. This torment, was extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grieuous; for that the Croſſe was very heauy, and contayned, as holy men obſerue, fifteene feet in le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth. Our Lord was all worne, and wounded, euen to his bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells; his ſtrength was vtterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed; and his ſhoulders vpon which the waight was laid, were flead. And now, if the onely tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15770:31"/>of ſuch a parte, with the hand, doth put a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to great grief and paine, what paine and grief would it cauſe to our Lord to lay ſo heauy a waight vpon a body ſo wearyed, and ſo wounded? And for as much as the Croſſe was longe, and would be dragging vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ground, by meeting with ſtones in the way and ſtirring by that meanes vpon his ſhoulders his paine and grief would be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed.</p>
            <p>In this ſorte went our Lord, with great ſorrow and paine, all that long way from <hi>Pilates</hi> houſe to <hi>Mount Caluary,</hi> which conſiſted of one thouſand eight hundred and ſeauenty two paces. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our Lord would worke no miracle, in carrying the waight of that Croſſe; but giue leaue that nature might ſuffer as much, as poſſibly it could; therefore,<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15770:31"/>when he had diſpatched a good part of the way, he grew to faint, and fall downe vnder the burden. And the prime men of the Iewes, conceiuing that there might be danger, leaſt he ſhould dy amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them in the way, gaue him <hi>Simon Cyrenaeus</hi> for a companion, who might helpe him to beare the Croſſe: &amp; ſo the aſſiſtence, which they affoarded him, grew not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clemency in them, but from a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to impoſe greater torments vpon him, by his dying, not there in the way, but on the Croſſe it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The ſorrowes and torments of that way being paſt, and he being the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> arriued at <hi>Mount Caluary,</hi> they began to giue him new torments. One was; that they ſtript him, by taking his owne cloathes away, ſo to put him naked vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Croſſe. Now this was a moſt painfull
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15770:32"/>thing to our Lord; becauſe his cloathes ſtucke faſt to his wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, by the meanes of baked and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gealed blood; and whenſoeuer they tooke them off with violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, they ſtill opened the wounds againe, they flead his body, and renewed all his former paines. To this was added that other tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which the cold ayre cauſed: for that penetrated into his body, vpon the opening of his fleſh, &amp; made him all quake and tremble, through the much cold he felt; and this torment laſted till he expired.</p>
            <p>The other torments which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vpon his nakednes were theſe. The ſoldiers tooke that moſt holy body, with extreame fury, and ſpred it forcibly vpon the Croſſe; &amp; applying his backe to the wood, and extending his armes and feet at length, they<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15770:32"/>beganne to nayle one of his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds; and the nayle being great, and not very ſharpe, it carryed before it through the hole, both of the skinne and of the fleſh. Then tooke they the other hand, and becauſe the body and the nerues were ſhru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke vp together, through the cold, they were faine to draw out the hand with violence, to make it reach that hole, which they had already made. They alſo tooke his ſacred feet, and they furiouſly ſtretched them forth to nayle them. And there be holy men, who deliuer, that for the nayling of his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, they gaue ſix &amp; twenty ſtrokes with the ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; and for the nayling of his feet, ſix &amp; thirty; &amp; that through the violence wherewith they drue his hands and feet to nayle them downe, the ioynts of his ſacred body were diſſolued, &amp; the bones<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15770:33"/>diſplaced, in ſuch ſorte, as that they might be numbred, one by one. O how great &amp; ſharpe, were theſe torments, to that moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate body? how did they euen parte his bowels, and euen pearce his hearte? Our Lord did very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally performe that which the <hi>Pſalme 21.</hi> had ſaid, <hi>They haue boared through my hands and feet,</hi> and they haue faſtened them with nailes to the Croſſe; and by reaſon that the parts of my body were ſo exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded one from another, and all the ſubſtantiall humour thereof ſo conſumed,
<hi>all my bones might be numbred.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As ſoon as his moſt ſacred body was nailed, they raiſed the Croſſe vp on high; and they ſuffered it to fall with great force, (together with his moſt ſacred body which was faſtened to it) vpon a hoale made in a ſtone, which was there<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15770:33"/>prouided for that purpoſe. This was another incomparable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for then all the parts of his body did euen open their ioynts; and his bowels did all quiuer; and the hoales of his hands and feet, did ſpred abroad, and beganne to ſtreame forth blood, like ſo many ſpringes. It is paſt expreſſion, to ſhew the greatnes of the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, which thoſe bleſſed armes endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, being nayled and ſo ſtrictly extended; and thoſe ſacred feet, which ſuſtained the waight of his whole body; &amp; that diuine head, which now had no reſting place but vpon thornes; and the paines which all thoſe parts of his body felt, euery one of them being out of the true place; and thoſe finally which were felt by that bleſſed ſoule of his, which carried vpon it, the immenſe weight of all thoſe torments together, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15770:34"/>after that manner, that ſoule being grown a very ſea of woe, for the ſpace of three houres; till expiring, he laid it in the hands of his eternall father.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>THE V. CHAPTER. <hi>Of the Patience, deſire, and loue, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Chriſt our Lord indured all thoſe torments, for the example and edification of our ſoules.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AL theſe immenſe ſorrowes and torments did Chriſt our Lord endure with a <hi>Patience,</hi> which was vnſpeakeable, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed only worthy of himſelfe. He complained not of his enemies, who treated him with ſo extreame cruelty; nay he defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe againſt them, nor was he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with them, nor did he ſhew them any cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance of diſguſt,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15770:34"/>nor did he ſpeake any one word, which might doe them any af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front, or offer them any threate, or put them to any paine. Nor did he ſo much as wiſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any hurt, but did both wiſh and ſpeake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignely &amp; mildly to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And he conſerued in his moſt dear heart, a great loue towardes them all, wherewith (for as much as they would be capable therof) he loued them; giuing them holy inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and offering them diuine ſuccours, and praying for them, &amp; wiſhing that they would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit thereby, and cooperate with them, and be conuerted to him, and ſo be ſaued. And he was euer ready to pardon them, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them to his grace, &amp; glory, if they would be conuerted to him.</p>
            <p>In this manner did Chriſt our Lord carry himſelf towards thoſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15770:35"/>enemies of his, who tormented him; and with this loue, and with this <hi>Patience,</hi> did he treate them. And he ſuffered thoſe paines and torments in ſuch ſorte, as that he did greatly deſire and delight in them; and he imbraced them with the extreame guſt of his hart; &amp; reioyced in the interiour part of of his ſoule with vnſpeakeable gladnes &amp; ioy, that he had them to ſuffer. And ſo when they laid the Croſſe vpon his backe, and when they nailed him to it, he intertayned it with ſo much ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite and guſt, as cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. Great is the contentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and affection, wherewith a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther embraces a moſt beloued ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, when ſhee findes him deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of a long and dangerous captiuity; and ſees him returne ſafe and ſound into her houſe. But incomparably much greater<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15770:35"/>was the contentment and guſt, wherewith Chriſt our Lord em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the Croſſe. For already there were paſſed, three and thirty yeares, ſince he had begunne to deſire, and loue it, with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe deſire and loue; that ſo he might worke the ſaluation of the world thereupon: and then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing, that his ſo long and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement deſire was to be ſatisfied, it cannot be expreſſed, how great guſt he had; when they laid and ſtrecht him vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Croſſe. And therfore, embracing it with thoſe bowells of his moſt tender loue, he would ſay to it in this manner, in the interiour part of his hart. O moſt happy Croſſe, how long is it ſince I haue loued &amp; deſired thee? it is now three and thirty yeares ſince I liue enamoured of thee, and I all enkindled with the flames of this deſire and loue,<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15770:36"/>to ſee myſelfe conioyned to thee. O thou moſt pretious wood, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the iuſt price for ſinne ſhall be payed, and the diuine iuſtice ſhall remaine fully ſatisfied, and my Father ſhall be perfectly glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, and man ſhall be ſaued, &amp; freed from ſinne and death, and eternall damnation; &amp; ſhal make his entry into the Kingdome of heauen: O with how good a will I ſuffer my ſelfe to be nayled to thee, and will ſo continue vpon thee, till I leaue to liue!</p>
            <p>And becauſe the affection and deſire which Chriſt our Lord had to ſuffer, was the cauſe of that vnſpeakable <hi>Patience,</hi> wherewith he endured all the ſorrowes and torments of the Croſſe, let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the teſtimonies of the Gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel wherin he declared the fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke will &amp; deſire which he had to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; and wherwith he offered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15770:36"/>to his Paſſion and death. He diſcouered this his pleaſure, in that he manifeſted and declared many times, and in particular manner to his diſciples, how he was to ſuffer in
<hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> and the torments &amp; kinde of death which he was to ſuffer. Once he ſaid thus to them. <hi>Matt.</hi> 16. It is fit that I goe to Ieruſalem, and that I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer many torments, at the hands of the Scribes and Phariſees, and chief Prieſts; and that I be put to death by them. And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> perſwading him, not to endure it, he reproued him in ſharpe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, for ſeeking to hinder his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. It is cleer, that ſince he knew ſo long before, what he was to ſuffer, he might haue auoided it, and fled from it, if he would: and ſince he did not ſo, it is plaine he had an affection and deſire to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:15770:37"/>Another time going vp to <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> ſome few dayes before that Eaſter, when he ſuffered, he ſaid thus to them. <hi>Matt.</hi> 20. <hi>Behould we are going vp to Ieruſalem, and the ſon of man is to be deliuered vp to the Princes of the Prieſts, &amp; to the Scribes, who will condemne him to death; and will deliuer him ouer to the Gentiles, to the end that he may be ſcorned, ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and crucified by them.</hi> As if he had ſaid; Behould, how without being carryed, or compelled, we goe, in a moſt voluntary manner to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> where thoſe thinges which concerne my Paſſion and death are to be accompliſhed; to the end that you may vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, how willingly I offer my ſelfe to that Paſſion and death, whereby I am to ſaue the world:</p>
            <p>He alſo diſcouered the great affection, and deſire which he had to ſuffer, by his going to that<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15770:37"/>garden, which was ſo notorious a place, and where he knew his enemies would ſeeke, and finde him out; as alſo, in that being there, and knowing that his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies came to apprehend him; he went not thence to ſome other place, where they might not finde him; but he went by that very way where they were cominge towards him; &amp; he went to meet them, and animated his diſciples to goe with him, ſaying. <hi>Matt.</hi> 26. <hi>Riſe vp and let vs goe; for he who will betray mee, is neer at hand.</hi> So ſaith Saint <hi>Ierome,</hi> when he declares theſe words. Our Lord we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter his perſecutors, without any feare at all of his Paſſion; and he voluntarily deliuered himſelf to them, that they might depriue him of his life, and he ſaid to his diſciples, <hi>Riſe vp, and let vs goe:</hi> as if he had ſaid; let not our enemies<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15770:38"/>finde vs heer like fearfull men; but let vs goe with good courage to receiue them; and let them ſee, the confidence and cheerfullnes, wherewith we offer our ſelues to death.</p>
            <p>Being gone forth to meet his enemies, and already ſtanding before them; and they hauing many lights wherby they looked vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him; &amp; he being well knowen to them, and eſpecially to Iudas: yet was it not in their power to know him then, becauſe he gaue them not that power, not concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with that faculty of their minde, wherby they were to haue knowen him; till ſuch time, as he diſcouered himſelfe to them by ſaying, <hi>It is I:</hi> declaring thereby, how truly it was in his owne ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or ſo much as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnles he would him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. So ſaith Saint
<hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:15770:38"/>Our Lord ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in the middeſt of his enemies, did blinde their eyes; &amp; this he did, to make them know, that not onely they could not haue apprehended him, but not ſo much as haue ſeen him, if himſelfe had not giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> power to doe it. He alſo declared thus much, by making them returne and fall backward to the ground, like dead men, and that with one onely word; diſcouering cleerly thereby, how eaſy a thing it had bene, for him to defend himſelfe from them, &amp; to take away both their ſtrength and life, if he had bene pleaſed. He had formerly bene in feare in the garden; to declare the weakenes of mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and by the immenſe loue which he bore to man, he ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came all that naturall feare; and he being ouercome by that very loue, and by the extreame deſire<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15770:39"/>which he had to ſuffer for the ſaluation of mankinde, we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t forth to receiue his enemies, as if they had bene his moſt beloued frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds. And firſt hauing made it plaine, that they could not once haue touched him, nor ſo much as haue knowen him, if he had not bene ſo pleaſed; he then gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leaue and power to doe what they would to him. And this he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by ſaying. <hi>This is your houre, and the power of darcknes.</hi> This is that hower, wherein liberty is giuen you, to the end that you and the Princes of darcknes, by your mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, may execute both his power, &amp; his cruell wil, vpon my perſon.</p>
            <p>This affection, wherewith Chriſt our Lord offered himſelfe to the torments of death, and this inuincible <hi>Patience</hi> wherewith he endured them, had bene prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied by <hi>Eſai</hi> 53. <hi>chap.</hi> in theſe words,<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15770:39"/>
               <hi>He offered himſelfe to death, becauſe he would.</hi> The ſame Prophet had ſaid, <hi>The eternall Father had layd all our ſinnes vpon Christ our Lord, to the end that he might ſatisfy for them all;</hi> and all thoſe ſinnes might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, &amp; conſumed by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his Paſſion. And inſtantly he declares the manner how he layd them vpon him, which was not by forcing, or conſtraining him to ſuffer; but by infuſing an immenſe charity into him, and by inſpiring, &amp; mouing his heart thereby to the end that volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily and freely, &amp; with extreame readines and gladnes he might offer himſelfe to death. And de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the <hi>Patience,</hi> wherewith he ſuffered that death, he ſaith; <hi>As a sheepe he opened not his mouth.</hi> So great was the
<hi>Patience,</hi> the deſire and loue, wherewith he endured the torments, which he tooke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:15770:40"/>him, for the diſcharge of our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that he opned not his mouth, either to defend himſelf, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of others. Like a quiet ſheepe, which bleyes not, when his throate is cut; ſo went he in ſufferance and ſilence, as he was carryed to death: and as an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and ſtill lambe, which is ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; quiet whileſt they ſheere him, ſo our moſt bleſſed Lord, did in quiet ſilence and repoſe endure that fierce outrage, wherewith his enemies tormented him, and that moſt cruell fury wherewith they put him to death. By theſe and other teſtimonies, did <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord declare the immenſe loue and moſt ardent deſire, which he had to ſuffer the torments and death, which he endured for man, yea &amp; yet to endure greater tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; to ſuffer more deathes, if his enemies had power to giue<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15770:40"/>him more; wheereupon wee may inferre, the vnſpeakeable <hi>Patience</hi> and ioy, wherewith he ſuffered them.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt ponder, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually meditate, with a very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and deep conſideration, vpon theſe examples of <hi>Patience,</hi> which ſhine in the life and Paſſion of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord; and thereby we muſt be animated to ſuffer &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure with true <hi>Patience,</hi> all thoſe euills of puniſhment, which may happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs in this life, how great or tedious ſoeuer they may be. For therefore (ſaith Saint
<hi>Efrem</hi>) the afflictions and tribulations of this life, ſeem grieuous and into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable to vs, becauſe wee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not the Paſſion and death of <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord. Let vs therefore allwaies carry before our eyes &amp; imprint in our hearts this death and Paſſion of his; and all thoſe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15770:41"/>examples, which he gaue vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in of <hi>Patience:</hi> and let vs imitate him, by ſuffering all the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions and penalties of this life with a good will. And ſince it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a ſoldier to follow his cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, with much labour and with offering himſelfe to troubles, and wounds, and dangers of death; though he be but a mortall man, who cannot giue him ſtrength wherewith to fight; nor can raiſe him from death if he ſhould by in the combat; nor can giue him, who conquers any other reward then ſome te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall thing of ſmall value; how much more is it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, that wee follow and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord, &amp; Sauiour, by ſuffering with <hi>Patience?</hi> Since he giues ſtrength to them, who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him wherewith to ſuffer, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts wherewith to do it cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; and deliuers them who imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate <pb n="69" facs="tcp:15770:41"/>him from eternall death, and and beſtowes the moſt excellent reward vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them of eternall life. For, as the Apoſtle ſaith, it is a word moſt faithfull, true, &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of all eſtimation, that, if wee dy with <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, that is to ſay, if wee dy to our ſinnes, and ill deſires, abhorring and morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying them, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord died to his corporall life; we ſhall lead a moſt glorious and bleſſed life together with him; And if we ſuffer the ſad and painfull things of this world, and euen death it ſelfe with
<hi>Patience,</hi> for the loue of <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord, and in imitation of him, wee ſhall reigne with him for euer in his celeſtiall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:15770:42"/>
            <head>THE VI. CHAPTER. <hi>Of the Patience wherewith wee ought to ſuffer the loſſe of temporall goods, and of the example which Chriſt our Lord gaue vs herein.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THough any one of the pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; torments, which were ſuffered by <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, may ſerue for a ſufficient motiue, to animate vs to endure all the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and tribulations of this life with
<hi>Patience;</hi> yet that kind of paine endured by him, which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries moſt reſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the Croſſe, which moſt vſually is to be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by vs, doth vſe to comfort &amp; induce vs beſt to ſuffer it: and for this reaſon wee will treat of ſome particular Croſſes, for which we may finde particular examples of <hi>Patience,</hi> in the Paſſion of
<hi>Chriſt</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:15770:42"/>our Lord. One of the ills of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, which happens ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily to men, is the loſſe of their eſtate, &amp; temporall goods, which befalles them ſometimes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are robbed; ſometimes they looſe them by meanes of fier, and ſhipwrackes; ſometimes by vniuſt ſuites in lawe; ſometi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes they are cooſened of them; &amp; ſometimes they are put to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice by the intemperate ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the yeare. By what way or meanes ſoeuer we growe to looſe our temporall goods, wee muſt eudure it with <hi>Patience,</hi> accepting it at the hand of God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming our ſelues to his holy will.</p>
            <p>The particular example which muſt comfort vs in this afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and giue vs heart to beare it with <hi>Patience,</hi> is to ſee that
<hi>Christ</hi> our Lord was vniuſtly ſtript of all his <pb n="72" facs="tcp:15770:43"/>cloathes in his moſt ſacred Paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by thoſe moſt baſe ſoldiers, who crucified him. He liued poore in this world; and becauſe he loued and extreamely delighted in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty, he poſſeſſed no temporall goods at all. Thoſe things which he receiued by way of almes to ſuſtaine his Apoſtles, &amp; to deuide amongſt the poore, he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready beſtowed. There remained no more to him, but his cloathes, and of thoſe they ſtript him, and left him naked: &amp; that nakednes was acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panyed with great cold, and great ſhame, which he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by remayning in that ſorte till he dyed. From others who are executed, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take not their cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes till they be dead; but from our moſt bleſſed Lord, they tooke his, whileſt yet he was aliue; and he was pleaſed to e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dure this being diſpoiled of his cloathes, and this<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15770:43"/>paine and ſhame in remaining naked, that he might ſuffer for vs, and withall might giue vs an example of <hi>Patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs therefore animate our ſelues by this example of Chriſt our Lord, to ſuffer any want, or loſſe of temporall goods: and let vs ſay thus in our owne hearts. Since <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Kinge of glory, and the vniuerſall Lord of the whole world, would needes, for loue of me, and for my ſaluation, endure pouerty and the want of temporall goods; &amp; was content that they ſhould ſtrip him of all his cloathes, and expoſe him na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to the ayre, and put him to the ſhame of appearing ſo to the whole people; moſt iuſt it is, that I, for loue of him, and for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mine owne ſoule, ſhould endure this want of meanes, and this loſſe, or wrong, whereby I am<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15770:44"/>depriued of the temporall goods which once I had. And let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider for the better exerciſe of our
<hi>Patience,</hi> that whatſoeuer preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice or temporall loſſe wee haue, doth come to vs from the hand of God, and for the good of our ſoules.</p>
            <p>This did <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer to vs, by another example, and teſtimony of the holy Gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell. <hi>Matt.</hi> 8.
<hi>Luc.</hi> 5. <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. He went into the country of the Gera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens, where he found two men tormented with diuells. He caſt the diuells out, and ſo cured the men by the power of his word. The diuells beſought him, that ſince he had caſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of thoſe men, he would giue them leaue to enter into a great heard of ſwine, which was feeding in thoſe fields hard by, and which belonged to the inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of that Citty. Our<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15770:44"/>Lord gaue them leaue to doe it, and inſtantly they poſſeſſed thoſe ſwine, which might arriue to the number of two thouſand, &amp; they carried them with extreame fury into the ſea, where they were drowned. Hereby wee are taught, that the diuells could do no hurt to the ſwine, vnles our Lord had giuen them leaue: as neither the diuell, nor any other creature, can doe vs any hurt at all, vnleſſe God giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> power to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and vnleſſe he worke by meanes of the diuel, or that other creature, which doth vs hurt, whatſoeuer it be. For though God be not the cauſe of any fault or ſinne; yet is he the cauſe of the puniſhment, which is brought on by reaſon of the ſinne or fault, &amp; is receiued by meanes thereof. So ſaith Saint <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> Since the diuels haue not ſo much as power<pb n="76" facs="tcp:15770:45"/>ouer ſwine, which are but the goods of men, it is cleer that they haue no power ouer men, who are made according to the image of God; and ſo wee haue no cauſe to feare the diuells, but onely God. And the ſame did he declare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the hurt which might growe to vs from any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that it alſo proceeds from the hand of God, ſaying,
<hi>Matt.</hi> 10. Two ſparrowes are of ſo little va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, that they are ſold for a toy, and yet God hath ſo particular care and prouidence ouer euery one of them, that not one can fall dead to the ground, or be taken in a ſnare, without his diſpoſition &amp; will. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how much more will he take care of men; and not conſent that any creature ſhould ſo much as touch them, either in ſoule or body, or ſo much as in their goods, without his leaue?<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15770:45"/>In this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner did <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord declare, that all ills of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, proceed to vs from the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of God.</p>
            <p>He alſo ſhewed, how he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daines them all, to the good of ſoules; that is, to the end that ſinners may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted, and iuſt perſons ſaued; becauſe he deſires not the death of a ſinner, but that he may be conuerted and liue; &amp; particularly he procures this, when he takes their goods from them, as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> notes, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus. When God viſits his ſeruants with the want of thinges neceſſary for this life, and makes them ſuffer hunger, or thirſt, as he proceeded with the Apoſtles, he failes not thereby of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe which he made them, that nothing ſhould be wanting to them. For theſe temporall goods, are helpes and kinds of Phyſicke<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15770:46"/>to the ſoule; and God is the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, who beſt knowes, when to miniſter them, and when to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue them; and ſo when they are wanting to vs, as they are many times, wee muſt knowe that God Almighty is the cauſe thereof, for the exerciſe of our vertue, and for the good of our ſoules. And ſpeaking in particular, of that which <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord did with the Geraſins, in depriuing them of their goods, when he gaue the diuells leaue to drowne their ſwine, Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith; <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not that liberty, by way of granting their deſire, or to performe their will; but to the end that the loſſe of their goods might be profitable to the owners for their ſoules, &amp; be an occaſion of their ſaluation. And the ſpirituall profit, which came to them hereupon, as Saint<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15770:46"/>
               <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> obſerues, was that they might knowe the power, which diuells had to doe men hurt, if God did not hinder them, and ſo they might be thankefull to him for defending them by his diuine prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; as alſo to the end that they might feare, and fly from ſinne, by meanes whereof, men grewe ſubiect to the power of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells, to be vexed by them in this life with temporall paines, and in the next with eternall torments.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the motiues &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which a faithfull Chriſtian muſt conſider, to the end that he may beare the loſſe of temporall goods with <hi>Patience;</hi> namely, the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord; &amp; that it comes from the hand of God; and for the good of his ſoule. And thus the loſſe of temporal goods, will be of greater profit to him, then the encreaſe thereof would<pb n="80" facs="tcp:15770:47"/>haue bene. For, that little tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall loſſe, will be the occaſion of a great ſpirituall gaine: The Saints of God, haue confeſſed &amp; experimented this truth. Whileſt the bleſſed <hi>Laurentius Iuſtinianus</hi> (he who afterward was Patriarch of <hi>Venice</hi>) was one day out of his Monaſtery, the houſe fell on fier; and that parte thereof was burnt, where he kept the prouiſions of food, which he had laid vp for the whole yeare. When the Saint came home from abroad, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious men tould him what had paſt, and they were afflicted by occaſion of ſo great a loſſe. But the Saint, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering how it came ordained by the prouidence of God, who ſo deerly loues vs, and who in all thinges procures the good of ſoules, and eſpecially of ſuch as ſerue him, receiued this loſſe with much contentment;<pb n="81" facs="tcp:15770:47"/>though not for the loſſe it ſelfe, but becauſe the will, and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Almighty God, was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed thereby. And ſo with a cheerfull contenance he ſaid to his Religious; What hurt is there, my children, in this which hath happened to vs? It is no ill, but good; it is no loſſe but gaine; ſince by meanes thereof, wee ſhall bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter execute our good deſires, in practiſing pouerty, and <hi>Patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a great benefit to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of God, and of much merit and value, when he may diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute his goods to the poore, and imploy them vpon the workes of mercy: but if he cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to looſe his goods, if they be ſtolne from him, if gotten away by iniuſtice, or loſt by any other accident, and if he accept of that loſſe with much <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> and with much content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the loue of God, and to<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15770:48"/>conforme himſelf with his diuine will, who ſo ordained; he ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily doth aduantage his ſoule more, and it doth merit more, and pleaſe God more by this courſe, then by the other. For this Act of the vertue of
<hi>Patience</hi> &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation is more pure &amp; free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe loue, &amp; thereby a man doth more deny and mortify his owne will, &amp; doth more exerciſe Faith and hope in God, as alſo the loue of his, and the eſtimation of his holy will. And ſo wee ſee, that our Lord hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away theſe goods by ſome ſiniſter accident from many Saints, which they would haue giuen away in almes; to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foard them meanes of greater merit thereby; and for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of that rare <hi>Patience,</hi> wherwith they accepted and loued their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity, and had guſt therein, as proceeding from the will of God.<pb n="83" facs="tcp:15770:48"/>Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the Patriarch of
<hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> a man of rare mercy tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards miſerable men, and euen a very miracle of mercy, ſent from <hi>Alexandria,</hi> to the Adriaticke ſea thirteene ſhips full loaden with marchandiſe, and thinges of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, which he had raiſed out of the Reuenues of his Church, that ſo they might be ſold in diuers parts remote, and the whole price be giuen by him to poore people in the way of almes, as his cuſtom was. Now it pleaſed Almighty God, that vpon the riſing of a great tempeſt at Sea, al the goods were caſt away, and the ſhippes returned empty to <hi>Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dria.</hi> And God did thus ordaine, becauſe he more eſteemed the great Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and
<hi>Patience,</hi> which the Saint would exerciſe in this wracke, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Mercy which he would haue exerciſed, if the goods had not<pb n="84" facs="tcp:15770:49"/>bene loſt. And ſo without all faile the profit, which the Saint drew from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, was admirably great; he receiuing it with a good will, and giuing God harty thankes for the ſame; and humbling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe much, by the knowledge of his ſinnes; in regard whereof he confeſſed, that God had ſent him that loſſe, to clenſe him more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly from thoſe ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Chriſostome</hi> teaches vs this truth, and confirmes it by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of holy <hi>Iob,</hi> ſaying thus; Nor onely the doing of good, but the ſuffering of ill, obtaines a high reward, in the ſight of God: and <hi>Iob</hi> ſeemes to haue profited more in vertue, by the afflictions which he endured, then by the good deeds which he performed. For really, it was not ſo illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious, &amp; ſo high an act in him, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the wooll of his ſheepe,<pb n="85" facs="tcp:15770:49"/>he clad the naked, &amp; ſet his houſe open to the deſtitute, that they might take parte of the goods he had; as when, hearing that the fier had conſumed his ſtocke, and that his houſe was fallen, and his fortune ouerthrowen, he accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of that loſſe, at the hands of God, and thanked him for it. And a greater victory did he obtaine of the enemy, and he confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him more, in giuing thankes to God vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loſſe of his goods, then in beſtowing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poore people. For certeinly it is an act of greater vertue, to endure the loſſe of goods with a generous &amp; gratefull minde to God, then to beſtow almes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poore. Nor is it a thing to be admired, for a man to giue God hearty thankes when he is in good eſtate, &amp; when things ſucceed proſperouſly with him; but vpon the arriuall of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chances,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15770:50"/>and in the loſſe of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall goods to giue harty tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks to God, and to eſteeme ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions for benefits, is a very admirable thing; and giues a very excellent teſtimony of great ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. This is the diſcourſe of Saint <hi>Chriſoſtome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs therefore ſerue our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of theſe examples, and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord and of his Saints, to make vs ſuffer all loſſe of temporall goods, with <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</hi> Let vs ſo much eſteeme of of the ſpiritual health of our ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, that whatſoeuer may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to vs for them, wee may value as a great mercy, and gift of God. And ſince the loſſe of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall goods, giues vs matter and occaſion for the exerciſe of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity towards God, by louing it becauſe he loues it; and for the exerciſe of <hi>Patience,</hi> by endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:15770:50"/>it and accepting it willingly becauſe God ſends it; and becauſe therby we diſcerne the loue which God carries towards vs, and the care he hath of our ſaluation (ſince he giues vs helpes, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters vs occaſions whereby wee may ſerue him the better and ſo profit more;) let vs eſteeme of euery temporall loſſe for a very great benefit, and mercy of God; and as for ſuch let vs thanke and praiſe him ſaying, with holy Iob. <hi>chap.</hi> 1. <hi>It is God who gaue mee</hi> this temporall bleſſing, <hi>and it is he who hath taken it away; as himſelfe was pleaſed ſo hath he proceeded with mee.</hi> Moſt iuſt and holy was his will, both in giuing it and in taking it, and his holy will the bleſſed for euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:15770:51"/>
            <head>THE VII. CHAPTER. <hi>Of the Patience, Wherewith wee are to endure corporall infirmities; and of the example, which Chriſt our Lord hath giuen vs herein.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ANother euill of puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and very vſuall and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the life of man, is corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall infirmities and feauers, and ſeueral other paines &amp; torments, and wounds, which he ſuffers; by reaſon whereof, he is in great need of <hi>Patience:</hi> &amp; we muſt fetch it alſo in this kinde, from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord. And though our moſt bleſſed Lord had no naturall infirmities at all; nor was it fit that he ſhould haue any, becauſe theſe are wont to proceed, from ſome defect of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, or natural faculty of the<pb n="89" facs="tcp:15770:51"/>body, or from ſome diſorder in life; yet all the paines, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his moſt ſacred Paſſion, may ſerue for a moſt efficacious motiue, to make vs ſupport all kinde of thoſe infirmities with <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> which may happen to vs in this life; and particularly the paine, &amp; torment of thirſt, which he ſuffered vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Croſſe, &amp; the being ſo forſaken &amp; abandoned, as then he was. For that which me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are much troubled with, in their ſickneſſe in their ſickneſſe is the paine and torment which ſickneſſe put them to; and the want of that aſſiſtance &amp; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, which is neceſſary for the cure, or eaſe at leaſt, of the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; &amp; al this was found extrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in that thirſt, which
<hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord endured vpon the Croſſe.</p>
            <p>The thirſt, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord ſuffered, was moſt veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; Firſt by reaſon of the incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable<pb n="90" facs="tcp:15770:52"/>labours &amp; vexations, which he had ſuffered all that day and the night before; and ſecondly, becauſe by the hurts and wounds, which they had giuen him, he had ſhed either all, or in a manner all the blood out of his veines; and by the waie as he went, and by the vexation and labour to which he was put he had ſweat away all the humour of his ſacred body, which then was growen all conſumed, and dry. And to this it muſt be added, that from the ſupper of the night before, and in all that day following, he had not dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke, ſo much as one drop of water. Now if any one of theſe thinges be wont to cauſe great thirſt, as wee ſee in men who are wounded, and haue ſhed much blood, and in them who haue laboured, and ſweat much, and in them alſo who haue not drunke of a long time<pb n="91" facs="tcp:15770:52"/>before: what kinde of thirſt ſhall that haue bene, which was endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord? Infallibly it was moſt extreame; &amp; the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which it cauſed, was grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, beyond any thing which we are able to expreſſe. And now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the paine and torment, which he felt thereby, he ſaid thus, I
<hi>thirst;</hi> and the remedy and comfort, which he obtained for the eaſe thereof, was, that one of the ſoldiers tooke a ſpunge, and wetting it in wine, which was ſpoyled and growen vineger, and mingled with gall, he tyed it to a long cane, and ſo applied it to his ſacred mouth; and our Lord tooke thereof, not to drinke it downe (becauſe it was not fit that he ſhould drinke of ſo deadly a thing) but he tooke it to haue a taſte thereof; he tooke as much as might ſerue to afflict, &amp; torment<pb n="92" facs="tcp:15770:53"/>his taſte; ſo to ſuffer the more for vs. So doth the deuout
<hi>Lanſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> declare, ſaying; Our Lord, vnderſtanding well, how bitter that drinke was, which they gaue him, did yet take therof, through his great loue to vs; not ſo ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it downe, but onely to afflict his tongue and taſte with bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes: that ſo he might take tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in that parte of him, from which ſinne grew in vs. For <hi>Eue</hi> committed her ſinne by taſting of the forbidden fruite, and by meanes of her ſinne, did
<hi>Adam</hi> ſinne; and ſo haue wee all done after him.</p>
            <p>Such a kinde of refreſhinge was allowed to <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord againſt his paine, and torment of thirſt, which was to encreaſe the ſame paine, and torment. So ſaith Saint <hi>Cyrill;</hi> In ſtead of ſome wholeſome drinke, which<pb n="93" facs="tcp:15770:53"/>might refreſh him, they gaue him a bitter and hurtfull drinke; and that curteſy, which they would ſeeme to vſe in giuing him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to take, was conuerted into cruelty, by giuing him ſo vile a thing. And this did Saint <hi>Luke chap. 23.</hi> ſignify, ſaying; that the ſoldiers, putting a ſcorne vpon our Lord, did offer him vineger. The Pſalme recounts the iniury and affliction, which hereby they put vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, amongſt the reſt of his torments ſaying. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. <hi>They gaue mee gall in ſteed of meate, and in my thirſt they gaue mee vineger to drinke.</hi> That is to ſay: they were ſo farre from hauing compaſſion of me in my miſeries; &amp; ſo great was the cruelty which they vſed towards me, that when I came with my Croſſe vpon my backe to the place of torment, in ſteed of ſome aromaticall wine<pb n="94" facs="tcp:15770:54"/>(ſuch as they vſed to giue dying men for their comfort) they gaue mee wine corrupted, and min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with gall, and mirrhe; which being ſo very thicke was become as a moſt bitter, and moſt hurtful meate. And being afterward nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon the very Croſſe, hauing my blood exhauſted, and I being totmented with thirſt, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the thirſt I had, they gaue mee vinagre mingled with gal to drinke.</p>
            <p>This was the torment of thirſt, which <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord ſuffered vpon this Croſſe, and thus was he content to be abandoned; and by meanes of this, and the reſt, which he endured there, all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are to comfort the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their corporall infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and muſt be animated to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure them, with <hi>Patience;</hi> to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate our Lord thereby, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme<pb n="95" facs="tcp:15770:54"/>themſelues to his holy wil. So ſaith Saint <hi>Gregory;</hi> To the end that ſicke perſons may conſerue the vertue of <hi>Patience</hi> in their ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, they muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the paines which our God and our Redeemer did ſuffer at the hands of his owne creatures, &amp; how many affronts, how many buffets, how many ſpittings, how many ſcourges, and how many thornes he endured for our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and particularly how, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow the ſweetnes of heauen vpon vs, he tooke, when he was moſt thirſty, the bitternes of gall for himſelfe. This is the ſaying of Saint <hi>Gregory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides this, <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by many examples, and teſtimonies of the holy Ghoſpell, how great bleſſings are contained in corporall infirmities; and how great fruites are gathered from
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:15770:55"/>thence by ſuch as endure them with <hi>Patience.</hi> By this meanes of ſickneſſe, he drew many to his Faith, and to his grace, and to the obedience of his Ghoſpell; and he cured them ſo, of many ſinnes. For when they found themſelues ſicke, they went in ſearch after health of the body; and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieuing, and doing penance for their ſinnes, they obtained alſo health for their ſoules. So doth the holy Euangeliſts informe vs often. For ſpeaking of thoſe woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who with great deuotion &amp; faith followed <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, Saint <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith.
<hi>chap.</hi> 8. Our Lord going to preach amongſt thoſe Citties, and townes, diuers woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men followed him, whom he had deliuered from impure ſpirits, &amp; cured of their infirmities.</p>
            <p>Some of theſe, were <hi>Marie Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen,</hi> and <hi>Ioanna</hi> the wife of<pb n="97" facs="tcp:15770:55"/>
               <hi>Chuſa,</hi> a lawyer of Herods, and
<hi>Suſanna,</hi> and many others. And they following our Lord, did ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply him out of their meanes, with neceſſaries for the ſuſtentation of his life. By theſe words, the holy Euangeliſt giues vs to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that their hauing bene ſicke, and cured by our Lord, was the way to make them beleeue in him, &amp; to follow him; both in body and ſoule. And of the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who was ſicke of a bloody fluxe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9. <hi>Marc.</hi> 5. and had found no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy by her Phyſitians. S. Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew declares the ſame; and that her infirmity had made her looke for remedy in <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord; &amp; to be beleeue and confide in him, with ſo liuely faith, that ſhee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained health both in body, and ſoule. And the ſame thing happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the paralitike, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. for whom the roofe of the houſe<pb n="98" facs="tcp:15770:56"/>was taken of, that he might be brought before our Lord: for his infirmity was the cauſe why he made himſelfe be carryed, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to him; and that he would beleeue in him, with ſorrow for his ſinnes, and ſo obtaine pardon thereof. The ſame alſo happened to innumerable other ſicke per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whoſe ſickneſſes were the cauſe, why they ſought out <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, and gaue eare to his word, and beleeued in him, and amended their liues, and obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned true cure of their ſoules.</p>
            <p>A great bleſſing of God, is this kinde of corporal infirmity, ſince it is the roote, and occaſion of ſo high a good, as it is for man to know his ſinnes, and to be ſory for them, and to obtaine a cleane and healthfull ſoule, and eternall happines afterward. Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> aduiſes ſicke perſons, to conſider<pb n="99" facs="tcp:15770:56"/>this well; that ſo they may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the great benefit of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and thus he ſaith. Let ſicke perſons conſider how profitable the ſicknes of the body is for the health of the ſoule, &amp; how great a gift of God it is. For it makes a man enter into himſelfe, and knowe his weakenes, and his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and the miſeries to which he is ſubiect. It makes him feare God, and reforme his life, that ſo by meanes of penance, he may be made cleane from his former ſinnes, and may be bridled and fortified towards the not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting others afterward. Saint <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Nazianzen</hi> relates how being one day preſent with <hi>Eudoxius,</hi> a holy man, who was ſicke; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting, at the requeſt of the ſicke man, the ſeauenty ſecond Pſalme, wherein the holy Ghoſt declares, how God is wont to viſit
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:15770:57"/>his ſeruants in this life, with the ſcourges of ſickneſſes, and other afflictions; that holy man (whom ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue to haue bene Saint <hi>Baſill</hi>) lift vp his eyes to heauen, and exclamed ſaying, I giue thee thankes ô celeſtiall Father, and Creatour of mankinde, for that thou doeſt vs good againſt our wills; that is, thou ſendeſt vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, &amp; other miſeries, which wee would not haue; whereby yet thou doeſt good to our ſoules; &amp; by exerciſing this exteriour man, which is the body, thou clenſeſt the interiour man, which is the minde; and thou carrieſt vs on towards eternall happines, by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities, and contradictions to our guſt. And Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> addes further, that the Saint ſpoke thoſe words, as reioycing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in his ſickneſſe.</p>
            <p>This diuine effect of ſickneſſe,<pb n="101" facs="tcp:15770:57"/>is thus declared in holy ſcripture by the mouth of the wiſe man. <hi>Prou.</hi> 20.
<hi>The ſigne of the hurt, and the ſecret woundes of the belly, doe cure mens euills.</hi> His meaning is, that both the exteriour hurts of the body, which are not very grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous; and thoſe alſo which are deep and dangerous, and doe pierce euen into the moſt inward parte of the bowells, doe clenſe the ſoule from ſinne. An admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mercy of God i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this, and a moſt ſingular teſtimony of his loue, and of the moſt ardent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire which he hath of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For man being forgetfull of himſelfe, and careleſſe of his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and in ſtead of vertue lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vice, &amp; not walking on tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards heauen, but towards hell; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God is pleaſed to viſit him with ſickneſſe, and tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt his will; whereby he <pb n="102" facs="tcp:15770:58"/>makes him enter into himſelfe, and to abhorre the ſinne which he loued before; and to forſake the way of hell, wherin he was going; and to purſue the way of heauen, which he had left; and to fly from many ſinnes, into which former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he had fallen. This is that mercy of God, which Saint <hi>Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus</hi> ponders ſaying. Almighty God, ſeeing that many men will not reforme themſelues vpon the motion, and at the inſtance of their owne will, ſends them ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities; that being troubled, &amp; afflicted, they may be amended, and ſo growe to loue thoſe things which formerly they loued not. And finding that ſome are ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined, and prompt to ſinne, he ſcourges them with infirmities of the body, to the end that they may giue it ouer; and he leaues them ſicke, becauſe it is better for <pb n="103" facs="tcp:15770:58"/>them to be broken by ſickneſſe, and paine, and ſo to obtaine the eternall ſaluation of their ſoules; then to liue full of health, and full of ſinne; and ſo to walke on towards hell. This is the ſaying of Saint
<hi>Iſidorus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe ſickneſſe doth not produce ſo excellent, and diuine effects in all Chriſtians, to take away their former ſinnes, and to hinder ſuch as are future; but onely in ſome, who when they are ſicke, doe enter ſeriouſly into their owne hearts, and haue contrition for their ſinnes, and change their liues; it is therefore neceſſary for all men, vpon ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing that they are ſicke, to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the eyes of their ſoule, &amp; to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine their conſciences well, and to conſider ſeriouſly of all thoſe thinges, which may giue impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to their ſaluation; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing<pb n="104" facs="tcp:15770:59"/>their ſinnes with ſorrow, giue a faithfull account of all to their ghoſtly Father; &amp; inſtantly put all things in order, with great diligence, which concerne the amendment and reformation of their liues; leaſt otherwiſe that ſickneſſe which God did ſend a man with loue and mercy, and to the end he might be clenſed from ſinne, and ſo be ſaued; doe not growe to ſerue but as a preface and beginning of thoſe endles torments, which are to be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by him, in the next life; as it will be to all them, who will not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by the ſickneſſes which God ſends. So ſaith the ſame Saint. The ſcourge of aduerſity and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, doth then clenſe the ſoule from ſinne, when the man changes his manner of life; for vnles he change his life, his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes remaine where they were.<pb n="105" facs="tcp:15770:59"/>So that, vpon the whole matter, euery ſcourge &amp; aduerſity, which God ſends a man in this life, is either to be as a ſpirituall Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory for his ſinnes committed, and of the penalty to which he is ſubiect for the ſame; or els it will ſerue for a beginning of that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paine, which he is to ſuffer afterward. For certainly, the pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and torments which are eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to be ſuffred by ſome, in the life to come, are begun to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſome of them, euen in this life.</p>
            <p>The truth which this holy Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor hath drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, carries great force with it: and the Holy Ghoſt therein doth teach vs, and confirme by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of many ſinners, that God did ſcourge them with great infirmities; and becauſe they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited not thereby, they paſſed on<pb n="106" facs="tcp:15770:60"/>from temporall paine and death, to eternall. And this ought to moue vs much, to receiue any ſickneſſe, as a moſt pretious gift of God, and to giue him great thankes for it, and to profit by it; making a change of our life to the better; to the end that, being cleer both of guilt and paine, we may make a ſhort and certaine entry into eternall life. And ſo, that may be fulfilled in vs, which
<hi>Eccleſiasticus chap.</hi> 3 ſaith. A great infirmity of the body makes a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s minde ſober; that is, it cleers it from ſinne, and doth moderate and iuſtify it in all thinges.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:15770:60"/>
            <head>THE VIII. CHAPTER. <hi>Of other great benefits, which are drawen from corporall infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, when they are borne with Patience.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BEſides this ſo excellent effect of clenſing and freeing the ſoule from ſinne, infirmity of the body vſes to produce diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which are very high, &amp; of incomparable benefit. Which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the ſoule, to the end that it may receiue giftes from God, &amp; that it may better and perfect it ſelfe more in vertue, and increaſe in merit; and that it may praiſe and glorify almighty God more, and that a man may ſo, become a particular inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the glory of God, which ſhines in him, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by his freeing him from that<pb n="108" facs="tcp:15770:61"/>ſickneſſe with particular proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and loue; or by giuing him admirable vertue and ſtrength, wherby to endure it with ſo great <hi>Patience,</hi> that it may be ſeen how it is God, who helpes him to endure ſo much, and with ſo good a will, in contemplation of eternall life.</p>
            <p>Thoſe blinde men to whom Chriſt our Lord gaue their ſight at his entry and iſſue out of the Citty of <hi>lericho. Luc. 18 Mat.</hi> 20. had neither ſeen his miracles, nor heard his doctrine; but had onely met with the fame of the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thinges which he did; and of the mercy which he vſed towards all; and thereby they grew to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in him, with ſo great faith, and deuotion, that, before all thoſe troopes, which followed him, they did with great cries, confeſſe him to be the true Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias, and the Sauiour of the world,<pb n="109" facs="tcp:15770:61"/>ſaying, <hi>Ieſus thou ſonne of Dauid haue mercy on vs.</hi> And after, when they receiued their ſight, they followed our Lord, praiſing and glorifying God. Many of the children of Iſraell, and of the wiſe and prudent men of the people, had heard the doctrine of <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord, and ſeen his miracles, with their owne eyes, &amp; yet they had not embraced his faith, nor had they bene moued by his works, to glorify Almighty God; whileſt yet theſe blinde men, by the onely fame of the workes of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, which had come to their eares, receiued his faith, and glorified and confeſſed our Lord. And the cauſe thereof was, in regard that the blindenes and pouerty of theſe men, made them more capable, and better diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to conſent to thoſe diuine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations, wherewith <hi>Christ</hi> our <pb n="110" facs="tcp:15770:62"/>Lord toucht their hearts, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them, to receiue the light of faith which
<hi>Christ</hi> our Lord offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; as alſo to the end that the fier of diuine loue, might more eaſily inflame their ſoules with true deuotion, and moue them to glorify the diuine Maieſty.</p>
            <p>The Ghoſpell expreſſes not, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord did pardon their ſinnes; or that he bad them ſinne no more, as he had done to other ſicke perſons; but that he gaue them light, both in body and ſoule, to the end that they might ſee and beleeue in him; &amp; deuotion, wherewith to confeſſe praiſe &amp; follow him. Vpon which wee may inferre, that they were already good men, and in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God: and ſo this is proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be that effect of ſickneſſe, which wee are now declaringe; Namely that it diſpoſes ſuch as<pb n="111" facs="tcp:15770:62"/>are good, to receiue new giftes from God, and to better them, and perfect them, by their grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in vertue, and by making the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> increaſe in merits, both of grace and glory.</p>
            <p>The bleſſed <hi>Euagrius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and diſciple of Saint <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charius,</hi> relates that; going one day in company of other ſeruants of God to viſit that moſt holy man <hi>Iohn</hi> a Moncke of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and a great Prophet, and much reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> as being one of the greateſt Saints of that time; one of thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſorts of his fell ſicke of a violent bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning feauer; and beſought the Saint to cure him. But the Saint made him anſwere in theſe words. Thou deſireſt to driue that from thee which it imports thee for the good of thy ſoule to keepe. For know, that as bodies are waſhed,<pb n="112" facs="tcp:15770:63"/>and clenſed with ſalt-peter, and other thinges of that nature, and doe ſo become more beautifull, and more pleaſing to the eye; ſo are ſoules more clenſed by corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſickneſſe, &amp; made more beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, and acceptable to the eyes of God. Thus ſaid this Saint. And this is the effect, which is produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by ſickneſſe, in good men; Namely that the ſoule growes thereby in purity, and grace, and in all thoſe vertues, whereby they are to pleaſe and ſerue God. And let vs now caſt our eyes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome other examples, which may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to vs, how ſickneſſe makes men become inſtruments of the glory of God, that ſo his power and goodnes may ſhine more in them.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord was cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who was borne blind, his diſciples asked him, <hi>10.9. what<pb n="113" facs="tcp:15770:63"/>ſinne it was, which had cauſed blindnes in that man, whether it were of him, or of his parents.</hi> Chriſt our Lord made them, this anſwere; <hi>That it was neither for his, nor his pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſinne; but to the end that the workes of God might be manifeſted in him.</hi> His mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was, that neither the actuall ſinne of him, nor of his parents, was the cauſe of his being borne blinde: nor was that blindnes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on him in puniſhment of any ſinne, which either his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents or himſelfe had committed; but he was borne blinde by the good will of God, to the end that by giuing him ſight, the world might growe to ſee thoſe workes, which were proper to the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; namely the working of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, by his proper vertue, which might teſtify and declare, that he who wrought them, was true God. By theſe wordes, did<pb n="114" facs="tcp:15770:64"/>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord diſcouer his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable goodnes, and libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and moſt ſweet prouidence, which ſometimes permittes ſmall inconueniences to arriue to the body; thereby to beſtow great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictions vpon the ſoule; and to honour his ſeruants, after an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary manner; making the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admirable inſtruments of his glory: as he proceeded with this blinde man, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he made blinde, to the end that, deliuering him by this miracle, it might grow pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, that himſelfe was the true God and Sauiour of the world; and that as ſuch, he might be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, and obeyed, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, both by that blinde ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who receiued the benefit, and by all thoſe others alſo, who would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by the notice thereof. And ſo by imparting a great bleſſing to the ſoule of that blinde man, by
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:15770:64"/>the light of faith, &amp; grace which he gaue, he declared the glory of his diuinity. Let vs produce an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other example of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. When <hi>Lazarus</hi> was fallen ſicke, his ſiſters ſent a meſſenger to our Lord; 10.11. who ſaid, <hi>looke heer O Lord, for he whom thou loueſt is ſicke.</hi> Now, in that <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> was ſicke, being ſo good a man, and ſo much beloued by <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord, wee are taught that ſickneſſe is a great gift, which God not onely beſtowes vpon ſinners for their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion, but alſo vpon iuſt and holy men, for the bettering of their ſoules, and for their encreaſe in grace, and merit; and therefore when God ſends ſickneſſe, it ſhould be receiued with a right good will. Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith, he who loues God, loues that which God loues; and therefore it is, that he loues <pb n="116" facs="tcp:15770:65"/>corporall ſickneſſe, which is the worke and gift of God. O how full it is of all reaſon, that a man who is the ſeruant of God, ſhould receiue that ſickneſſe which God ſends him, with a great good will, and a cheerfull heart! If a man being ſicke, God ſhould giue him health, he would receiue it very readily, and with much ioy and thanksgiuing; and yet certainly ought he to receiue that ſickneſſe, wherewith God viſits him: with greater affection, and thankesgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing: as being a moſt profitable gift of God. This is deliuered by Saint <hi>Augustine.</hi> And although it be true, that for the point of not ſinning through impatience, it ſuffices to endure, and beare the infirmity, without deſiring to be quit of it, by vnlawfull meanes, (as wee declared before;) yet to gaine and merit much more ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,<pb n="117" facs="tcp:15770:65"/>and to obtaine greater giftes, and graces from God, a man, as Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> faith, muſt receiue it with much contentment, and with a very affectuous manner of thankesgiuing. And it is fit that wee proceed after this manner, in regard that ſickneſſe is of much greater profit to many ſeruants of God, then health would be; and it is a great gift of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all; &amp; giues them meanes of much ſpirituall good; and for this reaſon doth God giue it to whom he loues, as he did to La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus, <hi>whom he loued much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Lord hauing receiued this meſſage from the two fiſters, ſaid to them who brought it; <hi>This ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is not to death, but for the glory of God;</hi> and to the end that the ſonne of God may be glorified by occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof. His meaning was, that that infirmity was not to end<pb n="118" facs="tcp:15770:66"/>in death; becauſe, though the man were to dy, yet he was not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue dead; but ſhortly to returne to this preſent life; and ſo it was not ordained for his death, but for the glory of God. And the particular glory of God, to which it was ordained, was, that the ſon of God, might be glorified by occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that ſickneſſe, &amp; death which followed thereupon; he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing life to the dead man, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect health to him who at that time was ſicke: &amp; ſo he was knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by meanes of that worke with faith and obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to be the true God and Sauiour of the world.</p>
            <p>By theſe examples did <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord diſcouer to vs, how the ſickneſſe of his ſeruants, might turne to his glory; which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens ſometimes by his freeing them from their infirmities, and from the dangers &amp; paines ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,<pb n="119" facs="tcp:15770:66"/>of, by ſuch particular and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary meanes of his diuine prouidence, as greatly ſerue to manifeſt the loue and care, which he hath of them; and inuite all ſuch as knowe thereof to praiſe, and loue, &amp; confide in his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes more and more. At other times (and this is moſt vſuall) this is performed by
<hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord in the ſickneſſe of his ſeruants, by his giuing them great and effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious fauours, &amp; ſuccours; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are made able to carry their infirmities with rare <hi>Patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> &amp; with admirable contentment. And ſo, whileſt they are ſicke, they performe high acts, and of great ſeruice to God; by meanes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, thee awake, and prouoke all men to praiſe and glorify <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, for working ſuch won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in his ſeruants. This ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious fruite of ſickneſſe, is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently<pb n="120" facs="tcp:15770:67"/>deſcribed, by that diuine <hi>Diadocus,</hi> in theſe wordes. As, for the making of a good impreſſion, by any ſeale vpon waxe, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary firſt, to ſoften that waxe, with the fingars, or with fier; ſo, to the end that the ſeale of diuine vertue, may be imprinted vpon the ſoule, &amp; that it may encreaſe, and growe perfect in vertue, and in the gifts of God, it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that it be exerciſed, and refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by infirmities, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tribulations, and troubles; whereby is may be diſpoſed, and ſoftened, for receiuing the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of this diuine ſeale. And iuſt, as in the primitiue Church, God wrought this glorious effect, in his ſeruants, out of the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Tyrants, and through the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, wherwith they afflicted, and martyred Chriſtians; ſo now doth God produce the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,<pb n="121" facs="tcp:15770:67"/>in the ſoules of his ſeruants, by meanes of temptations, and interiour aſſaults of the diuell; as alſo of exteriour and corporall ſickneſſe, and paine. I ſay, that in place of perſecutions, which are ceaſed, God ſends them the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations in their ſoule, and of ſickneſſe in their body; to the end that the image of diuine beauty may be made perfect in their hearts. It doth therefore much import, that wee receiue with great contentment the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and ſickneſſes, which God ſends vs; and that wee giue him thankes for them: for by this meanes they will growe to be a kinde of martyrdome to vs. This wee are taught by Saint
<hi>Diadocus.</hi> Let vs therefore be much anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to receiue any infirmities or tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which God may ſend vs, with a good will and let vs be<pb n="122" facs="tcp:15770:68"/>content to ſuffer them as long as it ſhall pleaſe God; not limiting him, either in the degree, or qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Croſſe; nor yet in the time, that it is to laſt. For it is God who knowes, what is conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for vs to endure; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee muſt remit our ſelues to his will, and reſigne our ſelues wholly, into his hands. For if (as Saint <hi>Ephrem</hi> ſaith) me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who haue beaſts, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which they cauſe their burdens to be laid and carryed from one place to another, doe well know, what waight or burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is able to beare, and that very burden doe they impoſe, and no greater: and if the potter, who makes veſſelles of clay, and puts them into the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of fier, doth well know how long they are to be kept there, to the end that, when they are taken forth, they may be well conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<pb n="123" facs="tcp:15770:68"/>and tempered, and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the vſe of man; and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine therein more time, then is conuenient, leaſt ſo they growe to be burnt vp, or broken; nor yet leſſe time then is neceſſary, leaſt ſo, they be taken forth too ſoft, and be ſubiect to looſe the forme they haue: how much more doth God, who is of infinit wiſedome and goodnes, and mainteines a moſt exact prouidence ouer all his creatures, and eſpecially ouer mankinde, know that iuſt burden of ſicknes, or other afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which euery one is able to vndergoe, &amp; beare, by meanes of that helpe which himſelfe is pleaſed to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foard; as alſo the time, during which it is fir, that he beare it? Nor will he impoſe more waight, then a man can carry, nor let it continue longer time, then it is fit for him to beare it; to the end<pb n="124" facs="tcp:15770:69"/>that he may growe a faithfull &amp; true ſeruant of his, and may be capable of that glory, which from all eternity, he had prouided for him.</p>
            <p>A moſt certaine truth it is, that God, of whom the holy Scripture ſaith, <hi>that he made all thinges, in waight number, and meaſure,</hi> and gouernes them all with ſo great ſuauity, and who well knowes the quality and degree of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, or other affliction which euery one is able to beare, either by that naturall or ſupernaturall ſtrength, which he hath receiued of him, as alſo how long he is able to beare it; will not impoſe a ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or other Croſſe, nor permit that it continue any longer time then he can ſuffer it with <hi>Patience;</hi> or then is fit for the good of his ſoule. So ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> Be not troubled about thy bodily<pb n="125" facs="tcp:15770:69"/>health; but deſire thou of God, that he will giue thee that which is moſt conuenient for thee: and ſo if he know, that thy health will be good for thee, he will be ſure to giue it thee; and if he giue it not, be thou well aſſured, that it would not haue bene good for thee. Wee ſee many, who being ſicke, conſerue themſelues cleane from ſinne; who if they had bene in health, would haue comitted many: and many men being in health, deliuer themſelues vp to great wickednes; who if they had bene ſicke, would haue auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſame. God doth well know what is fit for euery one. In this let vs place our chief care, that our ſoules may be, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue whole. This is deliuered to vs, by Saint
<hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs therfore herein, be very faithfull and true to God, and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:15770:70"/>very obedient to his diuine will: &amp; let vs ſo deſire health, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conueniency of this life, and ſo let vs beg it of God, as that wee may yet be ready ſtill, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue any ſicknes, or other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, at his holy hand, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he ſhall be pleaſed to ſend it; ſince our ſuffering theſe things with <hi>Patience,</hi> ſerues ſo greatly to the glory of God, &amp; to the good of our ſoules. And not onely, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the inconuenience which happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to vs, is very great, let vs eſteem it for a great mercy, and bleſſing of God, and full of profit to our ſoules; but alſo wee muſt thinke highly of it, &amp; value it as a great benefit, and of much profit and merit, euen when the ſickneſſe is not great. For, as the diuine <hi>Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brochius</hi> ſaith; whatſoeuer euill of puniſhment, (how light ſoeuer it may be) we ſuffer to the honour
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:15770:70"/>and glory of Almighty God, will be of greater benefit to vs, then if he had giuen vs the Empire &amp; dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the whole world. For whatſoeuer euill wee ſuffer with <hi>Patience,</hi> for the glory of God (how light ſoeuer it may be) God doth giue vs for the ſame, no leſſe thing, then himſelfe: For giuing vs his grace, he giues vs himſelfe with it; and ſo poſſeſſing the gift, we come to poſſeſſe therewithall, that Lord himſelfe of infinite goodnes, who giues it. Our Lord will not permit, that wee ſhould ſuffer aduerſities for his loue, without much profit and great reward: and ſo, by meanes of that which wee ſuffer, he communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates all that chief fruite of his moſt ſacred Paſſion, which are thoſe ſpiritual and celeſtiall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, through which we poſſeſſe God heer by grace, &amp; afterward<pb n="128" facs="tcp:15770:71"/>by eternall glory. And therfore doth God giue vs afflictions, and paines in this life; not becauſe our affliction or paine is pleaſing to him; but for that incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble benefit, which he knowes that wee ar to obtaine by meanes her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and which he ordained, from all eternity to beſtowe vpon vs, in reward of that <hi>Patience,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wee beare it. This is ſaid by
<hi>Rusbrochius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now by this conſideration muſt wee faithfull Chriſtians, be greatly moued, and encouraged to ſuffer corporall ſickneſſe and all other euills of puniſhment, with great contentment. For, if the diuell (as Saint Iohn <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome</hi> ſaith) when he propoundes to the heart of man, ſome tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary, and euen momentary delight, (the fruite and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof, are moſt grieuous<pb n="129" facs="tcp:15770:71"/>and eternall torments) doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and ouercome him ſo farre, as to winne him to expoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to ſo great a miſery, for ſo fle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der a delight; how much more is it reaſon, that wee, who are the faithfull ſeruants of <hi>Ieſus Christ,</hi> when he propoſes to our hearts, thoſe immenſe and eternall ioyes of heauen, be moued and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to receiue a ſicknes, or ſome other light and ſhort trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and to endure it with <hi>Patience,</hi> which bringes forth ſuch fruite, and reward after it, as is eternall life, and an euerlaſting kingdom of glory: and (aboue all) which produces the fruite of pleaſing, and glorifying Almighty God, which is incomparably the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt reward and fruite, which can be conceiued.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:15770:72"/>
            <head>THE IX. CHAPTER. <hi>Wherein it is confirmed, by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Saints, how great the fruite of ſicknes, and other tribulation is; and how this is an effect of Gods mercy, which he she was towards his friends.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BEcauſe it is of ſo great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to haue an vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, &amp; feeling of this truth; namely that it is a worke of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable loue in God to ſend vs ſickneſſes and other afflictions, which he expreſſes toward his greateſt friends, and he prooues and perfects them thereby; and makes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worthy of moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and moſt pretious crownes of glory, wee will confirme it by the example of ſome very emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Saints. <hi>Timothy,</hi> that holy<pb n="131" facs="tcp:15770:72"/>Biſhop, and the diſciple of Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> was ſicke of a paine in his ſtomacke, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. which is a grieuous and irkeſome diſeaſe, and had alſo many other infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> louing him much, and very tenderly, and well knowing the great need he had of health, that ſo he might with guſt, vndergoe all thoſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, which the office of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop exacted at his hands; did not yet take away this ſicknes, nor deſire of Almighty God that it be taken away. He cured other ſicke perſons, <hi>Act.</hi> 9. and that with ſo great facility, that it coſt him no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to put of his girdle, or to take out ſome handkercher, which had wiped of his ſweat, &amp; then to giue it, that it might be laid vpon thoſe ſicke perſons, and inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly the men were cured. And he obtained ſo very eaſily that<pb n="132" facs="tcp:15770:73"/>which he vſed to aske of God, as that begging once the liues of two hundred ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty and ſix per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who were going with him to Rome, and were in danger of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing by the way, God did gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the ſuite, and freed them from death at his requeſt: and yet to this diſciple of his, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he loued ſo much, he neither gaue health by miracle, nor did he beg the cure of God; but permitted him to continue ſicke as he was. And for ſome eaſe in thoſe infirmities which he had, he gaue noe other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ordinary remedy, which any vulgar friend, would haue preſcribed, ſaying: doe not ſtill drinke water alone, but take a little wine, for that paine of ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, which you endure; and for the many other infirmities which you ſuffer. But why then did not Saint <hi>Paule</hi> free his diſciple Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy<pb n="133" facs="tcp:15770:73"/>from theſe ſickneſſes? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knew, that they were great teſtimonies of the loue which God bore him; and that they were profitable to his ſoule, by occaſioning him to growe in <hi>Patience</hi> and humility and fauour in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> had many and grieuous ſickneſſes; &amp; in his age they were both greater, &amp; grew in effect to be continuall. Amongſt the reſt, he had the goute, which tormented him much; and ſo, as that he could not ſtirre, but carryed. And thus, howſoeuer he were of ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, his many acts of pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and continuall infirmities, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed him at laſt; and he came to dy, at the age of 65. yeares as <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar Baronius</hi> collects by the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Saint. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that he was ſtill ſo ſicke, he
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:15770:74"/>yet laboured much; and by thoſe labours he greatly benefited the Church; and by his infirmities, he greatly benefited himſelfe, for he carryed them with <hi>Patience,</hi> &amp; had much comfort therein.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> was tormented with moſt grieuous ſickneſſes; and ſometimes they brought him to the very dores of death. Yea they were ſo continuall, that the paine he ſuffered, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was beſt in health, might paſſe for grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſickneſſe in another. Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his Epiſtles, ſpeaks therof; and in one of them he ſaith;
<hi>I haue had many ſickneſses, and one of then hath ſucceeded another; and now I am alſo ſicke, and there is ſcarce an houre of my life, wherein I expect not my death.</hi> And in another letter of his, he ſaith; <hi>If when I am best, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the apparance, I haue of health) they account mee amongst them<pb n="135" facs="tcp:15770:74"/>who are giuen ouer; from thence it may be vnderſtood, what kinde of thing I am, when I am fallen into an expreſſe diſeaſe.</hi> And it was matter of great admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that vnder the waight of ſo many, &amp; ſo great ſickneſſes, he could labour ſo hard, by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, diſputing, preaching, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning, and going, as it were, in pilgrimage, to preach the Gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell in diuers parts of the world; &amp; that being ſo waſted with ſuch paines of body and diſtempers of blood, he ſhould not ſlack one whit in the care, and ſolicitude which he carryed, in effect, to all the Churches of the Eaſt; which were mightly perſecuted by heretikes. And by meanes of theſe infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that moſt holy Doctor, did mightily augment the merits of his moſt pure life.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> the Pope, was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed by Almighty God, with<pb n="136" facs="tcp:15770:75"/>extraordinary infirmities, and moſt ſharpe paines, which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued a long time with him. He had certaine ſeaſons of the goute, ſo long and tedious, and which gaue him ſo exceſſiue paine that in one pang thereof it continued with him, no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two yeares. He ſaith thus, in one of his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>I haue ſuch torment by the goute, that my life is grieuous to mee. I daily faint vnder my paine, and I expect the remedy of death. He had alſo in his body, an interiour ardour of heate, which did, as it were euen broyle, and dry vp his very bowells.</hi> And in all theſe infirmities, and torments, his heart was in ſuch conformity to the wil of God, &amp; he ſo greatly did deſire to ſuffer them, that he ſought not for comfort and eaſe of his miſeries in this life, but onely deſired it for the next. And he eſteemed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſingular bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,<pb n="137" facs="tcp:15770:75"/>and gift of God and was thankfull for them as being ſuch; as he declared in an Epiſtle which he wrote to Saint
<hi>Leander,</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Seuill,</hi> (who had written a letter to him, wherein amongſt other thinges he tould him, that he had bene much tormented by the goute) and Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him, after this manner. <hi>You tell mee that you are tormented by the goute; and my ſelfe am alſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly tormented by the continuall paine of the ſame diſeaſe; but it will be eaſy for vs to finde comfort in theſe miſeries, if wee call our ſinnes to minde, and conſider that wee are purged from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by theſe infirmities; and that ſo they are not meer ſcourges of God, but bleſsings alſo, whereby his diuine Maiesty doth vs ſo much good.</hi> With ſuch <hi>Patience</hi> as this, did Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> beare his ſickneſſes; and ſo they were of great helpe to him, for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:15770:76"/>of that moſt eminent ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity, and moſt profound humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and of that moſt plentifull light, which ſhined in his moſt holy ſoule. Of the inſufferable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, of Saint <hi>Iohn Chryſostom,</hi> and of the inuincible <hi>Patience,</hi> and conſtancy wherewith he ſuffered them, and loued them; and of the great merits, which he acquired by them, it would be a long bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe to write, and therefore wee will remit our ſelues to his hiſtory; and to his letters, where he ſpeakes of them.</p>
            <p>Almighty God gaue alſo to the holy Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> many grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, and dangerous ſickneſſes for the encreaſe of his vertue, &amp; for the greater purifying of his life. And yet, to giue more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe to the paine of his ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and of his ſanctity thereby, God ordained, ſo that ſuch reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies<pb n="139" facs="tcp:15770:76"/>as were giuen him for the eaſe of his paine, ſhould prooue to be of greater torment to him. For a certaine holy Biſhop, a friend of his, (through the feare he had, leaſt the Saint would not there be cured well, by reaſon of the rigour, which he was wont to vſe againſt himſelfe, tooke him out from the Monaſtery, wherein then he was, and deliuered him to an Infirmarian; who through ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance chanced to treate him ſo ill, and gaue him thinges ſo hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to eate, and ſo painfull to take; that euen men, who had bene healthy and hungry, would haue had difficulty therein. And if the Saint asked for one thing, the Infirmarian gaue him an other, very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he had need. Now the Saint endured theſe ſickneſſes, and this ill treatinge with ſo great <hi>Patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:15770:77"/>that he neuer complained, nor vttered ſo much as any one word of diſguſt; but obeyed that rude fellow, in all thinges, as any very obedient ſubiect would doe his ſuperiour.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Hugh,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne,</hi> had extreame paines in his ſide, which to any other man, would haue bene of great impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment, in the exerciſe of the Epiſcopall function; but he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered them with ſo great <hi>Patience,</hi> and ſtrength of minde, that he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured with that afflicted body of his, as if he had bene perfectly in health; and indeed it was a kinde of miraculous thing, how he could haue ſtrength and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to doe ſo much.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Dominicke</hi> had many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, and extreame paines in his ſtomacke, and yet through the great deſire which he had to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:15770:77"/>ſuffer, and well decerning, that thoſe were particular giftes of God, he had much ioy therein. And though whileſt he was ſicke, they did diuers thinges of much contradiction &amp; trouble to him; he neuer complained, nor ſhewed that he was offended thereby, but gaue God thankes for all.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Francis,</hi> beſides the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe he had, wherein he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to God, had after eight and twenty yeares, for the ſpace of twenty other yeares of his life, many grieuous ſickneſſes; and he ſuffered extreme paine in them. He had a ſorenes of eyes, which put him to extreame trouble; and once, through the paine thereof, he was faine to be ſhut vp fifty dayes, without being once able to behould any light at all, either by day or night; and the torment was ſo great, that he could take
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:15770:78"/>no reſt at all. He had extreame aches in his head, in his ſide, and in his ſpleen, &amp; he had alſo great burning feauers. His ſickneſſes and torments were ſuch, that he had not a parte of his body, which was not tormented with exceſſiue paines; &amp; his fleſh was ſo waſted, that his skinne did euen cleaue to his bones. And beſides all the reſt of his infirmities, he had a kinde of dropſy in his feet, which gaue him much affliction. So that his very diſeaſes were ſo painfull, that they may be accounted to haue brought him a tedious mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome full of torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Now this Saint, endured theſe infirmities with ſo admirable
<hi>Patience,</hi> that he neuer complained of them; nor, ſo much as ſhewed to be troubled at them; but he loued them, and reioyced in them; and through the great loue which he bare to<pb n="143" facs="tcp:15770:78"/>them, he called then his ſiſters; and he was wont to ſay, I giue thee thankes, ô Lord for theſe paines; and I beſeech thee, that if it be pleaſing to thee, thou giue mee a hundred times as much; &amp; this ſhall be of great guſt to me. For the guſt of my heart, conſiſts in this, that thy will may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed in mee. Saint <hi>Thomas of Aquine</hi> had great ſickneſſes. He ſuffred grieuous paines in his ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke; and he had a
<hi>Fiſtula</hi> in one of his legs; and he endured theſe infirmities with ſo great loue of God, and deſire to ſuffer, that he mortified himſelf, by forbearing to take ſuch things as might haue giuen him guſt, and eaſe. Being one day wholly without appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, &amp; thinking vpon a certeine fiſh, whereof he might well haue eaten; they brought it: but he, to mortify his ſence, did then refuſe<pb n="144" facs="tcp:15770:79"/>it; and God accepted this act of abnegation at his hands, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medyed his neceſſity by other meanes.</p>
            <p>The bleſſed <hi>Laurentius Iuſtinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> had grieuous and dangerous diſeaſes. Once they thruſt a hot iron through his necke, another time they opened a parte of his throat, with a razour. Theſe pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes were extreame, and the Saint endured the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſo great <hi>Patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> that neither did he complaine, nor ſigh, nor made any ſhew that he was in torment; but remained immoueable, as if it had not bene he, whom they burnt and woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but ſome other man. That which happened to thoſe Saints whom wee haue mentioned her, hath happened alſo to innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable others; namely to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed by almighty God with moſt grieuous ſickneſſes, to endure
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:15770:79"/>them with admirable <hi>Patience,</hi> &amp; to gather ineſtimable fruite from thence.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>THE X. CHAPTER. <hi>Of the fruite of the encreaſe of Faith, and Patience, which wee muſt ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Patience, which the Saints haue shewed in ſuffering their infirmities and paines.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FIrſt we may drawe from hence a very great and cleare teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, of the in fallible truth of the moſt holy Religion of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, which was profeſſed by all thoſe Saints. For to ſuffer ſo grieuous ſickneſſes, and ſo bitter paines, ſo many yeares, with ſo inuincible <hi>Patience,</hi> for the obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſpirituall &amp; inuiſible be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictions, doth incomparably exceed all the naturall power, and<pb n="146" facs="tcp:15770:80"/>ſtrength of man. And ſo wee ſee by experience, that men, who are voyd of the Faith of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not beare ſuch ſickneſſes and paines with true
<hi>Patience;</hi> but they faint and faile of courage therein; and they fall into great ſorrowes, and other diſorders a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt reaſon: and ſome goe ſo farre as to deſpaire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Silicius Italicus</hi> a moſt worthy man amongſt the Gentiles, and of great wiſedome and authority who had bene
<hi>Proconſul</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Conſul</hi> in
<hi>Rome,</hi> had a grieuous ſicknes, and was ſubiect therein to much paine; and not being able to endure it, and being ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenty and fiue yeares old, he kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himſelfe. And as <hi>Cato Vticenſis,</hi> (who went for ſo wiſe a man) not being able to endure the affront of being held to be ouercome by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> killed himſelfe, to be free
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:15770:80"/>from that affront: So did <hi>Silius Italicus,</hi> kill himſelfe to be freed from the paine of his ſickneſſe, which he was not able to endure. The Gentiles, who through their owne fault, were not aſſiſted by ſupernatural fauours from God for the ſuffering of ſuch paines with <hi>Patience,</hi> were ſubiect to this great weakenes, and impuiſſance in ſuffering them. And euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians, they who are not in the grace of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſuffer ſickneſſes and paines with great difficulty: and when they chance to be very great, men doe by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion thereof, commit many ſinnes, and fall into much diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der againſt the vertue of <hi>Patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</hi> Whereas wee ſee, that Saints and the ſeruants of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, endure moſt grieuous ſickneſſes, and intollerable &amp; moſt tedious paines, with ſo great
<hi>Patience,</hi> that<pb n="148" facs="tcp:15770:81"/>they loue them, and reioyce in them, and thanke God for them. And al the power of the ſickneſſe, and the fiercenes of the paine, can not make them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit any little errour againſt vertue; as we haue proued by ſo many examples. It is therefore a moſt clear, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine truth, that theſe men are greatly aſſiſted, and ſtrengthened by Almighty God, as true faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoules, and ſeruants of his; and that they are exalted by ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall fauours, both to doe and ſuffer thoſe things, which all the power and ſtrength of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature, can by no meanes doe, or ſuffer. For certainly <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man is in ſome great aduerſity, is a gift of God, as the Pſalmiſt ſaith,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 61. <hi>Patience comes to mee from our Lord.</hi> And S.
<hi>Auguſtine</hi> thus declares the reaſon, and root of this truth. Amongſt<pb n="149" facs="tcp:15770:81"/>wicked people ſo much more cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious is any of them towards the enduring the inconueniences of this life, as there aboundes in him more couetouſnes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence and loue of the world, in regard wherof he endures the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; amongſt iuſt perſons, ſo much the more couragious is any ſuch man to ſuffer paines and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as he hath the greater cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and loue of God in him, for whoſe ſake he ſuffers them. The loue of the world hath his roote in free will, being aſſiſted &amp; car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed on by the guſt and delight, which men take in thinges of the world; and the charity, and loue of God is infuſed by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: and ſo the
<hi>Patience</hi> of iuſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is a gift giuen by God, which was communicated to them by cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, whereby they exerciſe true <hi>Patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:15770:82"/>The ſecond fruite, which wee muſt gather from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, is a great courage and heart for the endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of any ſicknes, or afflictions, which it may pleaſe God to ſend vs; as alſo a firme confidence, that wee ſhall be able to endure them by Gods grace, with true
<hi>Patience,</hi> and to the great benefit of our ſoules. We know well indeed, that wee are not able to endure them by the only ſtrength of mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but by the fauour and helpe of God: and that God is ready to impart thoſe helpes and fauours in great abundance, &amp; with much liberality; and that, in fine, he will beſtow them vpon vs, as he hath done to all his Saints and true ſeruants. For ſo the eternall God (who is truth it ſelfe) hath promiſed, and ſo hath <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord merited for vs. And as the truth of God ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not faile, nor the<pb n="151" facs="tcp:15770:82"/>merits of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord be dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; ſo it is certaine, that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour cannot be wanting to vs, on the parte of God, if wee be diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to profit by it. Becauſe (as S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith) 1.
<hi>Cor. 10.</hi> God is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and true in the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his promiſes: and will not permit vs to be tempted with any affliction, or te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation which may be too heauy for vs to beare, and maiſter being aſſiſted with that grace, and fauour from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, which he is ready to giue vs for that purpoſe. But rather he will take care, that in the time of the temptation or tribulation, things ſhal ſucceed in ſuch ſorte, either by encreaſing our ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, or by diminiſhing our Croſſe, as that wee may be able to endure it; yea and to ouercome it at good eaſe, and reape much fruite, and merit by it. This is deliuered by <pb n="152" facs="tcp:15770:83"/>Saint <hi>Paule.</hi> And ſince, after the example of
<hi>Christ</hi> our Lord, and of his Saints, wee are reſolued to make the right vſe of theſe helpes from God, and to ſerue our ſelues of theſe fauours, and to doe on our parte, what wee can; wee may be confident &amp; aſſured (if we ſtill rely vpon that ſuccour from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen) that wee ſhall endure ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and all other Croſſes with
<hi>Patience.</hi> And that thoſe thinges, which it is impoſſible, or at leaſt very hard for our naturall weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to endure, will be made eaſy and ſweet to vs by theſe helpes from heauen; namely by the gifts of grace, and thoſe diuine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations, which God will impart to vs; to the end that wee may ſuffer them not onely with <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> but euen with ioy alſo, as the Saints did.</p>
            <p>Not onely muſt this hope en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage<pb n="153" facs="tcp:15770:83"/>vs to ſuffer, but it muſt greatly comfort vs therein. Saint Saint
<hi>Baſil</hi> declared it by theſe words. In the time of our tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wee muſt not ſeeke for helpe at the hands of our owne ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, or power, or riches, or authority, or humane glory; but at the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of God, who giues it to all ſuch, as ſeeke it. And with this confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God be glad if thou be ſicke; for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God loues, he cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects and betters by ſickneſſe: and if thou be poore, be glad; for God hath prepared eternall bleſſings for thee: and if thou ſuffer any affro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, eſteem thy ſelfe happy therein; for that affront will be changed into that glory, which the Angells enioy. Let vs therefore reſolue our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, not to make our firſt recourſe in our tribulations to humane helpe; and let vs not rely theron,<pb n="154" facs="tcp:15770:84"/>but haue recourſe to God with prayers, ſighes, and teares. Let vs place our confidence in him, and expect that from him: for he it is, who can ſaue vs. This is the ſaying of Saint <hi>Baſil.</hi> And by this very reaſon of hope, doth Saint <hi>Peter</hi> comfort vs ſaying. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. Do you greatly reioyce, ſince you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate with <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord in his afflictions and paines, by ſuffering in imitation of him, to the end that when after this life the glory of
<hi>Christ</hi> our Lord ſhall be manifeſted in heauen, you may alſo be made partakers thereof, and may exult in that ſupreme and euerlaſting ioy, becoming like him in glory, as you haue bene in paine.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb n="155" facs="tcp:15770:84"/>
            <head>THE XI. CHAPTER. <hi>Of the Patience wherewith diſcomforts and ſpirituall deſolations, are to be endured; and of the example which Chriſt our Lord gaue hereof.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THeſe ordinary <hi>euills of paine,</hi> of the remedy, whereof wee haue already ſpoken (ſuch as are loſſe of goods, and ſickneſſes) are common both to the good and bad; but there is another euill of paine, which vſually doth onely happen to ſuch as are good; and for the enduring whereof, they ſtand in great neceſſity to learne
<hi>Patience</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the example of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord. This euill, are thoſe diſcomforts, and dryneſſes, and ſpirituall afflictions, which God is wont ſometimes, to impoſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoules of ſuch, as do moſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially<pb n="156" facs="tcp:15770:85"/>ſerue him; to the end, that by the exerciſe of <hi>Patience,</hi> and humility, they may grow vp in vertue, and ſerue him better. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſeruant of God, who loues him much, doth treate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe with him by meanes of Prayer and Meditation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, and guſteth much in that familiar communication &amp; commerce with God, he findes by experience the vnſpeakeable dear ſweetnes of his loue; he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyes a moſt liuely feeling of his preſence, his goodnes; and his mercy; &amp; he poſſeſſes a moſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and ioyfull hope, and very intire promptitude of deuotion. Now it happens ſometimes, that this man, remaining in this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall paradiſe, and paſſing there a great parte of his pilgrimage in this life, God doth ſo ordaine concerning him, not onely ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times<pb n="157" facs="tcp:15770:85"/>but very often, and long together, that enabling him ſtill to mainteine and hould the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall parte of his loue, which conſiſts in louing that which he loues aboue all thinges, and in taking contentment therein, and in yeelding obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundments, and in carying a hatred againſt all ſinnes; and in vſing diligence to auoid them, &amp; in being watchfull and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue in the performing of all good workes; enabling a man (I ſay) to doe all this, God yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priues him of the experimentall knowledge &amp; guſt, which he had of him, and of his goodnes, and of the ſweet feeling of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and of the facility and eaſe which he was wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to finde in trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and communicating with him, and the readines of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, and the ioy which he was<pb n="158" facs="tcp:15770:86"/>wont to take in his hope. And though that ſoule remaine ſtill in grace, and friendſhip with God; and with a firme determination euer to ſerue him, and neuer to offend him; yet is it dry withall, and ſad and diſcomfortable, and full of feares, and aſſaulted by diſmaies, &amp; doubts. And though it be true, that this ſoule hath loſt nothing in point of vertue, or of the merit which it had, or of the loue wherewith it loued God and was beloued by him; yet in finding it ſelfe ſo altered, it feares leaſt it ſhould be hated and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned by Almighty God. This is the greateſt tribulation and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, to which good men are ſubiect in this life; &amp; that which they apprehend moſt: and <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord diſcouered both the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience, and the remedy in the holy Ghoſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:15770:86"/>The Apoſtles were full of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the ſociety of <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord, <hi>Matt.</hi> 14. <hi>Maro.</hi> 6. enioying the ſuauity, &amp; regalo of the ſight of his preſence, of the hearing his doctrine, and of the fauour &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilege of his Miracles. And our Lord hauing once wrought that Miracle of the fiue loaues of bread, whereby he had ſo parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly giuen them comfort, and done them honour, he ſeperated them from himſelfe; comanding them to imbarke them ſelues without him, and that ſo they ſhould tranſport them ſelues, to the other ſide of that ſea. The Apoſtles found this to be a very vntoward, and vnpleaſing buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and notwithſtanding that they obeyed, yet they did it with great repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, the thing being much againſt their minde. This was noted by the Euangeliſt ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.<pb n="160" facs="tcp:15770:87"/>He compelled and conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his diſciples that they ſhould enter vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſhip, without him; which is as much as to ſay, he made them enter perforce, and much againſt their will. And the reaſons of this repugnance in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was firſt, becauſe they would faine not haue wanted that ſweet preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of
<hi>Christ</hi> our Lord, which they did ſo deatly loue. For ſo ſaith Saint <hi>Chriſostome.</hi> Our Lord conſtrained his diſciples, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it was a thing ſo very hard for them to depart from him. Which grewe, without doubt, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that great ardour of affection which they carried towards him. Another reaſon therof might be the feare they had, leaſt wanting his preſence and fauour, ſome trouble or danger might happen to them at ſea. And thus alſo ſaith Saint <hi>Hierome.</hi> The diſciples had
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:15770:87"/>reaſon to depart vnwillingly, &amp; with much repugnance from our Lord, for feare leaſt in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence they might ſuſtaine ſome hurt, or incurre ſome hazard by ſea.</p>
            <p>The diſciples being departed from our Lord, and being em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barked and already vnder ſaile, there roſe a ſtiffe and contrary winde, which made them a high Sea, and brought a great ſtorme vpon them. The diſciples rowed hard, but could not aduance their backe a whit; and ſo paſſed the reſt of that day, and all the night following in great labour and hazard; till at length, toward the morning, our Lord did viſit and comfort them, &amp; make the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt ceaſe. By this difficulty the diſciples knew their owne weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; the great need which they had of our Lord; and ſo they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired<pb n="162" facs="tcp:15770:88"/>his preſence much the more. And when he had viſited them, &amp; freed them from that danger, they grew more in faith, &amp; hope, and loue of him; and ſo caſting themſelues all proſtrate at his feet, they cried thus out, with a more feruorous faith, and with more intire deuotion; <hi>Thou art cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the ſonne of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the departure which <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord cauſed his diſciples to make from him againſt their wil, he taught vs, how ſometimes he would parte his faithfull &amp; great friends, who ſerue him, and loue him, and haue much guſt in his preſence, from that dear com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of his. Not, for as much as concernes the friendſhip, which he beares them, nor for as much as concernes the ſtate of grace wherein they liue; but onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſweet comunication<pb n="163" facs="tcp:15770:88"/>which they had with him, and the ioy and comfort which they felt by his preſence. And this he doth very much againſt their will: but howſoeuer, he doth it yet for their good; to the end that they may growe to vnderſtand their weakenes better, and what poore thinges they would be without God; &amp; may become more hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and diſtruſtful of themſelues, and exerciſe themſelues more in
<hi>Patience,</hi> and haue a greater deſire and make a greater eſtimation of the gifts of God; and that when afterward, he ſhall viſit them, &amp; reſtore them to the gift of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull and dear preſence, they may grow vp in faith, and hope and loue of him. Thus ſaith Saint
<hi>Chryſostome.</hi> Our <hi>Lord</hi> ſuffered his diſciples to labour all night, by rowing, and to let their ſhip be toſſed from one ſide to the other;<pb n="164" facs="tcp:15770:89"/>that ſo they might deſire his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ſo much the more; and that the feare, and danger of ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke being paſſed ouer, they might confide the more in him, and carry him the more deeply impreſſed in their memory, and their heart.</p>
            <p>An other time <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord tooke his Apoſtles with him, and he put himſelfe with them, vpon the Sea; and laid himſelfe downe to ſleepe, in the pup of the ſhip; and whileſt he was ſleeping, there roſe ſo fierce a tempeſt, that it put them in danger of periſhing. And they, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiuing that becauſe our Lord was ſleeping, he ſaw not the perill wherein they were, came towards him, and awaked him ſaying; <hi>Saue vs Lord, for wee perish.</hi> Our Lord then roſe vp; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing reproued them for their lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle faith, he made the tempeſt <pb n="165" facs="tcp:15770:89"/>ceaſe.</p>
            <p>By this did our Lord diſcouer to vs the ſame myſtery, although in other termes. In that, when <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord was on ſhipboard with his diſciples, a tempeſt roſe; wee are taught, that whileſt he is preſent by grace with his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, who are iuſt, and holy men; the tribulation, &amp; temptation, &amp; the ſeeming to be abandoned by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God riſes vp againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And though our Lord doe well diſcerne the afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherein they are, and hath great care of them, and will be ſure, not to let them periſh; yet to their thinking, he hath little better then forgotten them; and it ſeemes to them, as if they were forſaken, and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned by him, and that they are in great da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of periſhing. Now our Lord proceeds thus with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for their greater good, to the end
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:15770:90"/>that they may the better knowe themſelues; and vnderſtand by experience of how little ſtrength they are in time of tribulation; and that, being freed from it by our Lord, vpon whom they call, they might the better iudge of the aſſiſtance and fauour which he affoardes them; and that they may confide more in him, and more admire his goodnes and power and diuine prouidence, and become more perfectly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to his heauenly will. So ſaith Saint <hi>Cyrill.</hi> Our Lord permitted, that a tempeſt ſhould riſe, for the exerciſing of the Apoſtles in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; and that knowing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the danger, wherein they were, they might frame the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er conceit of the power of the power of the ſame Lord; &amp; might reſorte to him, and place all their confidence in him. And although<pb n="167" facs="tcp:15770:90"/>they were in ſo great feare of peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, yet in very deed they were ſafe; nor was it poſſible that they ſhould be loſt, hauing that om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent Lord ſo preſent with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they had. This is deliuered by Saint <hi>Cyrill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that example of <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord, which is moſt proper to comfort his ſeruants in this kinde of tribulation, and to animate vs to ſuffer it with <hi>Patience,</hi> is that abandoning by the eternall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon the Croſſe; which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared when he ſaid thus, <hi>My God, my God, why hast thou forſaken mee?</hi> The eternall Father had not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken him, for as much as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned the grace and glory of his ſoule; nor for as much as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the vnion of the humane and diuine natures in him; but he abandoned him (according to<pb n="168" facs="tcp:15770:91"/>what we haue already declared) for as much as concerned the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible eaſe and comfort, which might flowe from the ſuperiour parte of his ſoule, to the inferiour parte of the ſame ſoule, and to the ſenſitiue parte of the body, which he ſuſpended, and detei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to the end that it might not redound vpon it, nor be commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to it; that ſo the paine of his Paſſion, might be the more pure, more grieuous, and more hard to be endured.</p>
            <p>By this abandoning, &amp; diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord, all the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God are to be hartened, and comforted in this kind of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of drynes and deſolation; conſidering, and diſcourſing with great waight of reaſon after this manner. Since the eternall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, did abandon his Sonne in his Paſſion, whom he infinitely <pb n="169" facs="tcp:15770:91"/>loued; depriuing him of all ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible eaſe and comfort: and ſince the Sonne himſelfe, would alſo haue it ſo, to the end that he might ſuffer ſo much the more for the loue of man; moſt iuſt it is, and moſt reaſonable, that the men of God who are members of the ſame
<hi>Christ,</hi> be alſo depriued at ſome time of ſenſible co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts; and that they may be afflicted, and forſaken, to the end that they may reſemble <hi>Christ</hi> himſelfe; and that the parts of the body may be like the head. Yea it is moſt reaſonable that they ſhould ſuffer this diſcomfort and deſolation euen gladly and with guſt, for the loue of the ſame Lord. Let them alſo conſider, that as <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord (though he were aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned by his Father) departed not as he was man, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vnion which he had with him by loue;<pb n="170" facs="tcp:15770:92"/>nor from the vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which he had with the diuinity; nor did he looſe one iote of the infinite grace, and immenſe glory, which he had in his moſt holy ſoule: ſo alſo his ſeruants (though they want thoſe ſpirituall feelings, and ſenſible comforts, &amp; though they be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted and afflicted) are not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore departed from the amity &amp; vnion with God; nor haue they loſt any parte at all of his grace and loue; but they continue ſtill his friends, and ſtill are pleaſing in his ſight; but by this exerciſe of humility, and <hi>Patience,</hi> they growe vp in all vertue, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, both of grace and glory.</p>
            <p>Moſt excellently doth <hi>Iuſtus Lanſpergius</hi> thus deſcribe theſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted ſeruants of God, of whom he had knowen many by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. Wee finde many friends of God in this world, who want
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:15770:92"/>all that ſenſible co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort in all the ſpirituall exerciſes of deuotion, which they were wont to enioy; ſo farre, as that ſometimes they can hardly once raiſe their ſpirit vp to God; and by a ſecret diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods prouidence, they ſeem to be (as it were) oppreſſed, with a great obſcurity of heart. And, notwithſtanding all this, for as much as concernes the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of vertue, they haue it, with a great feare to offend God; &amp; they fly from al kinde of ſinne, whether it be great or ſmall, with much care; and they watch very attentiuely, and keep ſtraight ward vpon their hearts, for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining the purity of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; complying exactly in all thoſe thinges, which they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerne the will of God; and they are truly mortified, and humble. Such perſons as theſe,<pb n="172" facs="tcp:15770:93"/>although they haue not thoſe feelings of loue, and ſenſible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, haue yet a true and liuely faith, whereby they liue, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect their courſe; &amp; they are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly great friendes of God, though themſelues doe not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it ſo. This is ſaid by <hi>Lanſpergius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let therefore the ſeruants of God, be comforted in this kinde of tribulation, and be encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to beare it, with <hi>Patience;</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing to take it at the hand of God; and reſigning themſelues to his diuine will; to the end that he may doe, and diſpoſe of them, as ſhall be moſt pleaſing to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And let them remaine firmly perſwaded in their very hearts, that ſo long as they conſerue a hatred againſt ſinne, and a firme reſolution to comply with the commaundments of God, (and
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:15770:93"/>that chiefly for the loue of him, and through an effectuall deſire and will to pleaſe God in thoſe thinges which he hath ordained) although they be much afflicted withall, and loue without any comfort or ſenſible feeling of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, yet in truth they are the friends of God; they are in the ſtate of grace; they walke on to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſaluation, &amp; eternall life; they are pleaſing to God by their good workes; and he will neuer aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don or forſake them. For thus hath he promiſed, to ſuch as with loue perſeuer in his ſeruice, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to euery one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he ſaid
<hi>Ioſue 1. and Heb. 13. I will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee, nor take my hand off, from thy defence.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb n="174" facs="tcp:15770:94"/>
            <head>THE XII. CHAPTER. <hi>Of the neceſsity, and fruite of Patience; and how it is a ſigne of the elect and predestinated of God.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BY many waies did <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord declare the great fruites and merits of <hi>Patience,</hi> in his holy Ghoſpell; Firſt by hauing ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that tribulations and aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities ſhould be the way to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; which cannot be well borne, and without diſadua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage to the ſoule, but by the vertue of <hi>Patience.</hi> This ordination of his did he diſcouer to vs, in that himſelf being come into this world to ſaue it, and to reſtore man to the grace, &amp; glory of the eternall Father, which man had loſt by ſinne, he was pleaſed, that his moſt holy life ſhould be aſſaulted and exerciſed (from the<pb n="175" facs="tcp:15770:94"/>firſt inſtant of his birth, to the laſt when he expired vpon the croſſe) by many perſecutions, &amp; aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of many kindes. And this is that, which was ſignified by
<hi>Simeo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Luc.</hi> 2. when taking the infant <hi>Ieſus</hi> into his armes, he ſaid to the Virgin; <hi>This infant shall be ſet vp for a ſigne, which shall be contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</hi> Chriſt our Lord was the ſigne of mans reconciliation to God, and of the pardon of ſinne, and of eternal life: for <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord wrought all this. And as a <hi>cauſe</hi> is a ſigne of the <hi>effect,</hi> ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, was the ſigne of all the good, which came to man; and of that mercy and loue, which God ſhewed him: but yet withall, he was a ſigne contradicted, by the diuell, and by the world. A ſigne he was, againſt which al the louers of the world, and all maligne ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits did, by their meanes, dart
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:15770:95"/>forth the arrowes of perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, of iniuries, of torments, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, both in word &amp; deed.</p>
            <p>This is that way, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord choſe for himſelfe in this world: and ſince all the elect, and predeſtinated of God, are to be like <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord (as Saint <hi>Paul. Ro. 8.</hi> declareth ſaying, <hi>They whom God elected and approued from al eternity, he ordained that they should be like his ſonne, who is the perfect image of the eternall Father</hi>) it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that they all muſt walke in the way of tribulations and aduerſities, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord did; to the end that being partakers of his Paſſion, they may alſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the honour of the ſonnes of God, &amp; the glory of being kings in heauen. This is explicated by Saint <hi>Gregory,</hi> in theſe words. He asketh what is the reaſon, why God afflicts and abaſes them in<pb n="177" facs="tcp:15770:95"/>this life, impoſing contempt, and paine vpon them, whom he hath elected from all eternity, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo very high and glorious in the Kingdome of heauen. And he anſweres his owne queſtion thus; Becauſe God ſees that he is to recompence, and reward men with ſuch immenſe and eternall benedictions in heauen, for this very cauſe doth he afflict them, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning theſe inferiour things of the earth; depriuing them of things of ſmall value, and infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting paines vpon them, which laſt not long. Since therefore it is ſo certainly true, that a man can not beare the aduerſities of this life to the profit of his ſoule, and with the fruite of vertue, and the merit of eternall glory, but by fortifying his heart through the the vertue of <hi>Patience;</hi> it followes, that <hi>Patience</hi> is that thing, which<pb n="178" facs="tcp:15770:96"/>carries men on with ſecurity, and certeinty, through the right way to heauen, which is that of tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; and that conſequently, the ſame
<hi>Patience</hi> is the marke of ſuch as are elected, and predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by Almighty God. For all men both good, and bad, haue aduerſities &amp; tribulations in this l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, though ſome more, then others; and therefore the onely hauing them, is no ſigne of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination; but the ſuffering the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with <hi>Patience,</hi> that indeed is the ſigne, which diſtinguiſhes them, who are elected and predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch others as are not ſo.</p>
            <p>This did holy Iudith <hi>lib. Iud. c.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. confeſſe ſaying, that all they who haue bene pleaſing to God, haue paſſed faithfully through many tribulations. He ſaith not that they only had tribulations, but that they perſeuered, faithful<pb n="179" facs="tcp:15770:96"/>therein to God, and obedient to his diuine will; which ſignifies, that they exerciſed true <hi>Patience,</hi> in their tribulations. This very ordination did our Lord diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer alſo, in that being able to caſt all thoſe damned ſpirits into the bottomles abiſſe of hell, and to keepe them ſhut vp there till the end of the world, without giuing then power to goe once out from thence; yet he doth not ſo, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes them liberty to goe forth, &amp; to remaine in the aire amongſt men; though yet withall, (for as much as concernes themſelues) they carry the very paine of hell about them. Of this wee haue a teſtimony in the Ghoſpell. For <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord being in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the
<hi>Geraſens, Luc.</hi> 8. and hauing caſt a legion of diuels out of a certaine man; they beſought him, not to caſt them into hell,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:15770:97"/>which he graunted, &amp; ſo he gaue them liberty to poſſeſſe a heard of ſwine, which they drowned. And that liberty, which our Lord gaue to thoſe diuels, to remaine here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he allowes to innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable others; &amp; he doth it, to the e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that they may aſſault me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſeuerall temptations; that ſo they may exerciſe
<hi>Patience,</hi> and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, by ſuffering their attempts; and by ouercoming the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the diuells. So ſaith Saint
<hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> The diuells deſired of <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord, that he would not caſt them downe into that bottome, that is, out of the world into that darkenes and Abiſſe of Hell, as the diuells had deſerued; and our Lord forbore to caſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe, and ſuffered them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in this world, to the end that vertuous men might not looſe thoſe crownes of glory,<pb n="181" facs="tcp:15770:97"/>which they were to gaine, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting thoſe diuells, and by fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them, and ouercoming their temptations.</p>
            <p>Since therefore for the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the perſecutions, &amp; vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of diuells, &amp; reſiſting their temptations, and continuing in combate againſt them, the vertue of <hi>Patience</hi> is ſo neceſſary; it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes that it is the fruite and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of <hi>Patience,</hi> to conſerue the ſoule in ſuch ſorte, as that it may receiue no hurt from temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and aſſaults of the diuell; and to encreaſe their merits in heauen, by the victory ouer thoſe temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; and thereby to manifeſt by an experimentall way, who are truly iuſt, and elect of God. So doth the holy ſcripture declare to vs in many places. It ſaith in <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiasticus, c.</hi> 27. <hi>As the furnace of fier, tries the pots of the potter, ſo doth temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation<pb n="182" facs="tcp:15770:98"/>and tribulation try iuſt men.</hi> The meaning is, that as the hot bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning furnace doth examine and declare which veſſells are good and fitly tempered, and which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are they, which being caſt into the fier, are not cracht or broken therby, but remaine hard and whole, and fit for the vſe of man; and as it doth alſo ſhew, which other of them are ill made, for they cracke, and breake, in the hot furnace; ſo doth temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and tribulation, whether it be offered by diuels or by men, declare and ſhew who are iuſt, and holy. And theſe are they, who through the euills and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which they endure, are not broken or ouercome by impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or other ſinnes; but through the vertue of
<hi>Patience,</hi> perſeuer firme and conſtant, in the practiſe of vertue, and the keeping of the lawe of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <pb n="183" facs="tcp:15770:98"/>
            <head>THE XIII. CHAPTER. <hi>How pleaſing the vertue of Patience is to God, and of the great fauours which he affoardes them, who ſuffer with Patience.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ANother way, whereby <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord declared the fruit, and merit of <hi>Patience,</hi> is, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular fauours &amp; extraordinary benefits, which he vouchſafed to to men, who ſuffered aduerſity, with
<hi>Patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Chriſt</hi> our Lord came to the <hi>Piſcina</hi> of
<hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and amongſt ſo many ſicke perſons as he found there, he imparted only to one of them, who had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained there ſicke eight &amp; thirty yeares, ſo great a fauour, and ſo illuſtrious a benefit, as it was, both to cure his body, and to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify his ſoule. And the cauſe, why<pb n="184" facs="tcp:15770:99"/>our Lord beſtowed this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, rather vpon him, then any of the reſt, was becauſe he endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his ſickneſſe, with more <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> then others. As is plaine, in that he, hauing bene ſicke ſo many yeares, made no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint, but anſwered ſo meekly to what was asked. Saint <hi>Chryſostome</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues this, and ſaith;
<hi>Christ</hi> our Lord, <hi>Io. 5.</hi> did not aske the ſicke man if he had any deſire to be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as if he had doubted of his will; but only for the manifeſting of his <hi>Patience,</hi> who hauing been eight and thirty yeares, and daily hoping for health, which he could not finde, did yet neuertheleſſe continue without going away, and deſpaired not being there; &amp; to teach vs alſo, that the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> why he cured rather him then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, was his great <hi>Patience.</hi> Let vs declare another exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to the
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:15770:99"/>ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord <hi>Io.</hi> 9. cured a man, who was borne blinde; and for the conſtancy, where with he confeſſed the ſame Lord, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended his truth, the Phariſees did perſecute, and affront him, both by word and deed; and they caſt him, as an excommunicate perso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, out of the Sinagogue. The good man obeyed this vniuſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, &amp; endured that wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with <hi>Patience;</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord, who knew it al, ſeeing the afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherein his faithfull ſeruant was, &amp; the <hi>Patience</hi> wherewith he bore it, ſought him out of ſet purpoſe, and ſpake to him after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, with great affability &amp; loue. <hi>Doeſt thou beleeue in the ſonne of God?</hi> which was as much as to ſay; Wilt thou beleeue, that he who cured thee, is the true so<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God? And euen as he was ſpeaking theſe<pb n="186" facs="tcp:15770:100"/>wordes, he did withall infuſe a moſt excellent clear light into the moſt inward part of his ſoule, to make him know and beleeue, that he who had cured him, was not onely a Prophet, and a Saint (as already he had confeſſed him to be) but alſo the true, and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſonne of God; for the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion did import ſo much. And ſo he beleeued, and asked; <hi>Who is he O Lord?</hi> And that Lord anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him thus. <hi>It is euen he who is ſpeaking with thee.</hi> Then inſtantly he fell proſtrate, &amp; adored him.</p>
            <p>This ſo admirable fauour, to ſeeke him, and comfort him, and honour him, and communicate ſo great light of faith &amp; grace to him, did God vouchſaffe to this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for his hauing been ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in confeſſing him, and ſo patient in ſuffering that wrong, which they had done him in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard<pb n="187" facs="tcp:15770:100"/>of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord. So ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſostome</hi> they who with <hi>Patience</hi> ſuffer the iniuries which are impoſed on them, for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining the truth of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, theſe men are greatly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured, and honoured by him; as wee ſee by the example of the blinde man, whom the Iewes caſt out of the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple: for the Lord of the very te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple ſought him out, &amp; he receiued him with great loue; and, as a ſoldier who had fought valiantly, he crowned him with a crowne of ineſtimable worth and beauty; ſuch as was the eminent grace, &amp; pawne of heauen, which he beſtowed vpon him. So great account as this doth <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord make of a faithfull, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient man; and ſo much doth he eſteem him, that omitting many others, he ſeekes him out with care, he comforts him by his<pb n="188" facs="tcp:15770:101"/>words, he ioyes his heart by his preſence, he honours him by his fauours, and he aduances him by his gifts. This doth Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> obſerue in theſe words. The Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, by relating, that <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord ſought out the blinde man, whom he had cured, giues vs to vnderſtand, that he was diligent in harkening him out, becauſe he found more faith and vertue in him, then in others; whereby wee may inferre, that he more eſteems one iuſt perſon, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ten thouſand ſinners. This wee are tould by S. <hi>Thomas.</hi> And though it be no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggeration at all, to ſay that God doth more loue one iuſt man, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole world of ſinners put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether (ſince abſolutely ſpeaking he onely loues ſuch as are iuſt, with the loue of grace;) yet conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how greatly God eſteems the ſaluation euen of ſinners, and<pb n="189" facs="tcp:15770:101"/>the care he hath to conuert them, to ſay that God more loues to ſaue &amp; fauour one iuſt man then many thouſand of ſinners, is no ſleight expreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but doth greatly diſcouer the particular prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and care, which God carries to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards iuſt perſons; and it giues matter alſo of much confidence to them who ſerue him, that through his goodnes they are to be greatly fauoured, and aſſiſted by him towards their ſaluation</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord did alſo diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the value, and fruite of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> in this, that when he would vouchſaffe any great vnuſual be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits to any, he firſt diſpoſed and prepared them, by the exerciſe of <hi>Patience.</hi> He was pleaſed <hi>Matt.</hi> 15. to feed foure thouſand men with ſeauen loaues of bread; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would impart this benefit to them, he made them ſtay three<pb n="190" facs="tcp:15770:102"/>daies, in the patient ſufferance of hunger, &amp; the paines of being in a deſert; and continuing to heare his diuine word. He was pleaſed to feed fiue thouſand me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with fiue loaues of bread; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would allow them this Regalo, he made them ſtay till towards might; when his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſayd, Lord the houre of ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is come, and gone; let theſe troupes diuide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues amongſt theſe neighbouring villages, that ſo they may haue meanes to eate. When already they had exerciſed their <hi>Patience,</hi> by ſuffering hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, he vouchſaffed to ſhew them ſo great a mercy as it was, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh them with a plentifull and ſweet food; whereby their bodies were ſuſtained; and he alſo made faith and confidence encreaſe in their ſoules. So ſaith Saint <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſostome. Thoſe troupes of people decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red<pb n="191" facs="tcp:15770:102"/>their faith by ſuffering hunger, and expecting till the euening.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this ſorte doth God impart illuſtrious fauours, to ſuch as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, and exerciſe <hi>Patience,</hi> in their aduerſities and troubles: &amp; to whom he is pleaſed to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaffe particular fauours &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, he ſends croſſes and tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, that ſo exerciſing <hi>Patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> therein, they may grow more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, and be more worthy of the eſpeciall gifts and graces, which he will impart. So ſaith Saint <hi>Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus.</hi> Then are the eyes of our Lord behoulding iuſt perſons with greater piety and mercy, when they are afflicted, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted by the wicked; and then doth he prouide greater bleſſings for them and more eminent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of glory, when once they are tried by ſome tribulation which they ſuffer with <hi>Patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:15770:103"/>Let not therefore any man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that when he is afflicted, he is forgotten by Almighty God; nor that he hath loſt the vertue, and grace he had, when he is aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and perſecuted by men. Let him not permit the diuell to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him, who would faine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him to this errour: but let him be very confident, that God hath then a more particular care of him; and loues him more, and comunicates more gifts, &amp; more ſingular fauours to him; and that then he growes vp more in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, &amp; augments his merits both of grace and glory. Thus ſaith Saint
<hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> Let vs not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it to be a ſigne, as if God did forſake, or forget, or eſteem vs little, becauſe he ſends vs ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities, or troubles; but rather let vs hould it for a moſt certaine toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he hath particular care <pb n="193" facs="tcp:15770:103"/>of vs; and that then he is to ſhew vs greater mercies, when he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts and tries vs. For if we haue committed many and very grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſinnes; wee may free our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues from them by <hi>Patience,</hi> and thanksgiuing in tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which grows from a contrite heart. And ſuppoſing, that we ſhould not be liable to thoſe many grieuous ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; yet by ſuffering tribulation with a thankefull minde, we ſhall obtaine moſt abundant grace at the hand of God. For ſo good he is, &amp; ſo liberall in doing vs good, that when he ſends vs any aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, he giues vs matter to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe more vertue; that he may ſhew vs more mercy. This is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to vs by Saint
<hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this ſo excellent, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable effect of <hi>Patience,</hi> which is exerciſed in tribulations, <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord declared, when he ſaid,<pb n="194" facs="tcp:15770:104"/>
               <hi>Io.</hi> 15. <hi>I am the true vine.</hi> For as much as concernes the nature of man, which I haue taken, I reſemble ſome very fruitfull and perfect vine, which yeelds moſt excellent fruite.
<hi>My celeſtiall father is the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band man;</hi> it is he who planted this vine of my humanity, and who cultiuates the ſame; he it is who made mee man, and who placed in mee the immenſe fullnes of grace and glory, which I haue; &amp; he who workes all that fruite in mee, which either I doe, or ſhall herafter yeeld. Euery bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch; that is euery man, who being vnited to me by faith, ſhall not yet yeeld the fruite of a good life, my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will cut off from me; either whileſt he is to liue, by letting him fall into errours, whereby he will looſe his faith; or els when he comes to dy, by deſpoyling him of thoſe ſupernaturall giftes<pb n="195" facs="tcp:15770:104"/>(through which he was once vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to mee) and alſo of power to doe penance, and ſo to be ſaued. And euery branch; that is to ſay euery true faithfull man, who is vnited to mee through faith quickened by charity, who ſhall produce the fruit of good works, <hi>my father will purge</hi> by celeſtial do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and by inſpirations, and interiour gifts, and by aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties alſo and tribulations; that ſuffering them with <hi>Patience,</hi> and charity, he may yeeld both faire, and moſt abundant fruite of holy actions, &amp; moſt pleaſing to God, and full of profit to ſoules; which ſhall deſerue moſt pretious gifts of grace, &amp; be crowned with that moſt ſublime reward of eternall glory.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <pb n="196" facs="tcp:15770:105"/>
            <head>THE XIIII. CHAPTER. <hi>Of the meanes, whereby the vertue of Patience may be obtained; which is, that wee be watchfull to conſider the fruite thereof, and the examples whereby wee haue been taught it by Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NOt only did <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord inſtruct vs by his example, concerning the neceſſity, which wee haue of <hi>Patience,</hi> and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and merits thereof; but he alſo taught vs the meanes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee are to obtaine it; and of this wee are going now to ſpeake. And becauſe wee treated thereof abundantly in another booke, we will heer content our ſelues, to declare briefly ſome examples, whereby <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed vs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:15770:105"/>The firſt meanes towardes the receiuing and ſuffering with <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> all the euills of puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which may happen to vs in this life, is that we be prepared and armed with the particular know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and conſideration thereof: It would not faile to be matter of moſt grieuous affliction &amp; paine to the diſciples of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, &amp; (euen the greateſt which they euer felt in this world) that their Maſter muſt ſuffer ſuch a death; &amp; therfore our moſt bleſſed Lord did arme them for it long before, announcing his Paſſion to them many times. At the firſt, he tould them of it thus, in couert termes;
<hi>Io.</hi> 2 <hi>diſſolus this Temple, and I will build it againe in three dayes and Io.</hi> 3. <hi>As Moyſes lifted vp the ſerpent in the the deſere, ſo muſt the ſonne of man be raiſed up on high.</hi> After this he ſpake of it in a more diſtinct and cleer<pb n="198" facs="tcp:15770:106"/>manner ſaying once, <hi>Matt.</hi> 16. I <hi>must goe to Ieruſalem to ſuffer and dy;</hi> and another time, <hi>Matt.</hi> 20.
<hi>Luc.</hi> 18. <hi>Behould wee aſcend to Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and the ſonne of man is to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered ouer to the Gentiles, and he is to be ſcorned, and ſcourged, and ſpit vpon, and crucified.</hi> In this manner did he giue them notice of his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, a long time before, that ſo they might be prouided, and prepared to endure it; and that, when it ſhould be preſent to them, they might not be ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized, nor troubled, nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maied thereby; but might endure it with <hi>Patience.</hi> So ſaith Saint <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome.</hi> Our Lord ſpake often of his Paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his diſciples; prouiding them againſt the temptation, to the end that they might not be ſcandalized, when the perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould arriue, and ſhould ſee the ignominy of the Croſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:15770:106"/>He alſo aduertiſed them a long time before, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23. <hi>Luc.</hi> 21. of the paine and perſecutions, and torments, and death, which them ſelues were to ſuffer in their owne perſons, for preaching that Gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, which they were to carry, throughout the world. For thus he ſaid. <hi>You shall be perſecuted, and vexed, and brought before Iudges; who in reſpect of mee, will torment, and sake your liues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you.</hi> Hauing prepared them with the notice of theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, which were to grow vpon them, he made them knowe, that
<hi>Patience</hi> was the remedy which they muſt procure, to the end that by thoſe croſſes, they might receiue no hurt, but rather inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable benefit. And he ſaid thus to them. <hi>One haire of your heads shal not perish; and in Patience you shall poſseſſe your ſoules</hi> Which was as if he had ſaid; Although you may <pb n="200" facs="tcp:15770:107"/>haue many enemies, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full oppoſits; yet ſhall you be ſo aſſiſted &amp; defended by Almighty God, who takes moſt particular care of you, that you ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the leaſt hurt thereby; and by the <hi>Patience</hi> which you ſhall haue in your tribulations, (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in expectation of celeſtiall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictions, you ſhall remaine firme and conſtant in my ſeruice, to the very end) you ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and ſecurely poſſeſſe the ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſpirituall life of your ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les; till you carry the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the glory of heauen.</p>
            <p>This is the firſt remedy, which muſt be vſed, for ſuffering the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of this life with <hi>Patience;</hi> namly that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his owne heart reuolue, and conſider with attention, what miſeries and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities may happen to him in this life; whether they be ſicknes,
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:15770:107"/>pouerty, iniuries offered by men, temptations of diuells; or elſe troubles and difficulties in any bodies particular office, or ſtate. And let him perſwade himſelfe, that if they come vpon him, they ſhal come ordained by Almighty God, and for the good of his ſoule; yea and that it is greatly fit for his ſaluation, that they come vpon him. For they are meanes, where by Almighty God doth addreſſe, and order his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination. And let him accept of them from that inſtant, for that very time when they may chance to come; and let him diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him ſelfe with courage to receiue them willingly, and with thankesgiuing, when they ſhall be ſent. For a man being thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided and prepared, will, receiue and ſuffer them with more <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> and aduantage of his ſoule.
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:15770:108"/>So ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome. The ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity which comes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men ſuddenly, and vnexpected; is wont to be very grieuous, and much felt; but that which is conſidered before it comes, and for which wee are ready and prepared, is more eaſily endured, when it arriues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another meanes for ſuffering tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with <hi>Patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> is ſeriouſly to conſider and ponder the moſt happy ſucceſſe which they haue, and the concluſion which they make, when they carry themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues well therein; to the glory of God, &amp; their owne greateſt good.
<hi>Christ</hi> our Lord gaue this remedy to his diſciples, for when he tould them things which troubled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he inſtantly alſo told them of that comfort and glory, which was to follow vpon that paine. When he tould them ſometimes, that the ſonne of man was to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, <hi>Matt.</hi> 16.
<hi>and</hi> 20. and be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied<pb n="203" facs="tcp:15770:108"/>in
<hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> he inſtantly alſo added that moſt glorious end of his Paſſion, and death, by ſaying; <hi>And the third day, he shall riſe againe.</hi> And when he ſaid thus in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. <hi>you all shall ſuffer ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall this night, vpon my occaſion,</hi> he added immediatly after, <hi>But when I shall be riſen from the dead, I will goe to Galile before you.</hi> As if he ſhould haue ſaid, neither will I remaine in death, nor ſhall you periſh in that ſcandall; for I will riſe from the dead, &amp; you being free from all danger ſhall follow mee. And
<hi>Matt.</hi> 13. <hi>Luc</hi> 21. hauing annou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced the extreme perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, which they were to ſuffer for preaching the Ghoſpel, he tels them withall, of the admirable fruite which was to grow to them thereby, namely the very prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching it ſelfe of the Ghoſpell, ouer the whole earth; and that it<pb n="204" facs="tcp:15770:109"/>ſhould be beleeued, and receiued by all the nations of the world. It would ſeem, that from ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments of perſecution, and death of the preachers themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, it might follow that they ſhould not be able to preach the Ghoſpell, nor perſwade any body to imbrace it; and yet wee ſee, he ſaith, that ſo great fruit would follow, that it ſhould be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and receiued ouer the whole world; and that all nations were to be ſaued by their faith in it, &amp; their obedience to it.</p>
            <p>This is that which wee are to conſider, and ponder in our tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, namely the admirable fruite, and glorious end, to which we arriue thereby, and in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation hereof, wee muſt animate our ſelues to ſuffer, not only with <hi>Patience,</hi> but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ioy. So ſaith the bleſſed Saint <hi>Marke</hi> the <hi>Ermite.</hi>
               <pb n="205" facs="tcp:15770:109"/>When you ſhall be vexed, and ſhall haue receiued ſome tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall loſſe, or ſome affront, and diſhonour, doe not looke onely vpon the preſent ill, but caſt alſo your eye vpon thoſe diuine fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of grace, and glory, which hereafter you are to receiue for that ill; &amp; you will certainly finde that you ſhall gather abundant fruit from tribulation; and that he who perſecutes you, will proue the Author of great benedictions to you both in this <hi>life &amp; the next.</hi> This alſo is aduiſed by
<hi>Eccleſiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus c. u.</hi> ſaying. In the daies of thy proſperity, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber thy miſery; and in thoſe of thy miſery, call thy proſperity to minde; for an eaſy thing it is, for God to giue euery one his paiment, &amp; reward, according to his workes, in the houre of his death. His meaning is this, as Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> declares;<pb n="206" facs="tcp:15770:110"/>In the time when thou haſt either temporall or ſpiritual proſperity, remember the afflictions which may happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thee, either in body or ſoule: that ſo thy proſperity may not make thee proud, but that thou mayeſt be conſerued in humility. And ſo alſo, in the time of thy aduerſity, whether it be ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall or temporall, remember the bleſſings of grace, and diuine conſolations, which thou haſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed at other times; and thoſe alſo which afterward thou maieſt receiue: that ſo thou be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maied, nor ouercome with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, but maieſt ſuffer all kinde of affliction, with
<hi>Patience,</hi> and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage.</p>
            <p>By this conſideration, doth S. <hi>Paule</hi> animate vs, to endure all the tribulations, and aduerſities of this life, with contentment and ſtrength of minde; ſaying thus; <hi>1.<pb n="207" facs="tcp:15770:110"/>Cor.</hi>
4. All the trouble and tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of this life, how long ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it may be accounted to laſt, doth yet paſſe away eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and is but light how heauy ſoeuer it may ſeem; and (as a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious cauſe, which is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and riſes from the grace of <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord,) it workes in vs an ineſtimable and moſt ſublime waight of glory, beyond all that which can be expreſſed, or euen conceiued; and which is not to be temporall, but eternall.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <pb n="208" facs="tcp:15770:111"/>
            <head>THE XV. CHAPTER. <hi>Of other meanes whereby wee are to obtaine, and conſerue the vertue of Patience, namely to conſider our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and to reſort to Almighty God, for the remedy thereof.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ANother, meanes which wee muſt vſe for the conſeruing of
<hi>Patience</hi> in aduerſity, is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the many ſinnes which wee haue committed in this life; and how iuſtly we deſerue the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, which we ſuffer for the ſame, and indeed all theſe, which may poſſibly come vpon vs in this world; and to moue our ſelues to compunction for the ſame, and euen to a deſire, that wee may be puniſhed for them by Almighty God, with mercy in this life. <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord himſelfe, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed<pb n="209" facs="tcp:15770:111"/>vs of this meanes, in the holy Ghoſpel. There fell a Tower neer the Poole of Siloe, by the Citty of
<hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which killed eighteene perſons; <hi>Luc.</hi> 13. and againe after this, ſome of the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lileans,</hi> being in oblation of the Sacrifice of certaine beaſts, <hi>Pilate</hi> ſent out a ſquadro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſoldiers who killed them, and ſo mingled their blood with the blood of the beaſts which they had ſacrificed. Now when they related this accident to
<hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, he ſaid thus to them. <hi>Doe not conceiue, that thoſe Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lileans were the greatest ſinners of all the Galileans, in regard that this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity of ſuddene death came thus vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them; for it is not ſo: but I ſay to you, that if you doe not penance, you all shall perish.</hi> And ſo alſo <hi>doe not thinke that thoſe eighteene men vpon whom the tower of Siloe fell, were the wickedst men who d'welt in Ieruſalem;
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:15770:112"/>for it is not ſo, but I declare to you, that if you doe not penance you all shall perish.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By theſe diuine ſpeeches, <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord taught vs two thinges. The one, that thoſe ſad accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and deaths, which men call di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſtrous; doe many time come, in the way of puniſhment for ſinne; but yet, that God doth not alwaies puniſh ſinners in this life, with ſuch calamities as theſe; but he doth often, either reſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their puniſhment in the other world, or els expect that they ſhould voluntarily doe penance, and ſo inflict ſome puniſhment vpon themſelues in this life. And ſecondly, he lets vs knowe, that when ſuch afflictions and tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations happen to others, we muſt be ſure to enter into our owne ſoules, and to conſider the ſinnes which wee haue committed, and
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:15770:112"/>how iuſtly wee merit all kinde of puniſhment for them; &amp; we muſt conceiue in our hearts, a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and grief, for hauing committed them; &amp; in penance, and ſatisfaction for the ſame, we muſt puniſh and mortify our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, with penall workes; and be willing to accept whatſoeuer troubles or tribulations, it may pleaſe God to ſend vs.</p>
            <p>A moſt certaine truth it is, that God ſends aduerſity to his true, and faithfull ſeruants (who yet haue ſinned in this life) to the end that ſuffering them with <hi>Patience,</hi> they may diſcharge, and ſatisfy for thoſe ſinnes, which they haue committed. As that holy Virgin
<hi>Sara</hi> confeſſed, ſaying, <hi>Iob. 3.</hi> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be thou ô God of our fathers; for that when thou art offended with vs, and doeſt ſend vs trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and afflictions, it is then, that
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:15770:113"/>thou ſheweſt great mercy towards vs; For in the time of tribulation, wherby thou puniſheſt, thou par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doneſt the ſinnes of them who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke thy name with a true heart. Thus doth God proceed with ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by meanes of tribulation. Some who are in ſinne, he induces by this meanes to do penance, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they grow to be free from the offences, into which they had fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len; and ſuch as are in the ſtate of grace, he occaſions to exerciſe <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> whereby he deliuers them from thoſe penalties, which they had incurred for their former ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And ſo great care hath God, to ſhew this mercy to this elect, that he permits other men, either through ignorance, or malice, to afflict and trouble them; and by occaſion, and vnder the title of faults which they haue not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, in the ſight of God. Iuſt<pb n="213" facs="tcp:15770:113"/>as the brethren of <hi>Ioſeph, Exod.</hi> 1. who finding themſelues to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, and puniſhed in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> for the ſuppoſed offence of being ſpies, which they had not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; came to know that indeed God ſent them that puniſhment, for the ſinne which they had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, in ſelling their brother. And ſo they confeſſed it ſaying. <hi>This punishment is iustly inflicted on vs; for wee haue ſinned againſt our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and this trouble is come vpon vs for that ſinne.</hi> Saint <hi>Eſrem</hi> relateth of himſelfe that being a boy and going into the fields to play, he hunted a calfe of another mans ſo hard; and threw ſo many ſtones at it, as that he killed it at length. And walking about a moneth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, through that field againe, he fell out to take him reſt amongſt ſome ſhepheards, who were loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to their flockes; a parte of<pb n="214" facs="tcp:15770:114"/>which flocke was wanting that night, for it had bene ſcattered by ſome rauenous beaſts. The Lords of the flocke, thought they had been theeues, who did that hurt, &amp; that <hi>Efrem</hi> was ſome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merade of theirs. They accuſe him, and take him for a theefe. And whileſt he was in priſon and much afflicted, an Angell appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to him in his ſleepe, demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the cauſe of his being there. He anſwered, that he had been taken, without any fault of his. Then the Angell ſaid; I know well that thou art free from any fault in this; but remember that thou madeſt a fault not long agoe, in killing the calfe of that poore man; and ſo thou wilt ſee, that now thou art iuſtly taken &amp; made priſoner in the part of God; and that his iudgments are very iuſt. He alſo tould him of others, who<pb n="215" facs="tcp:15770:114"/>were there impriſoned, for offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which indeed they had not committed; but they had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted other ſinnes, in regard whereof God ſent them that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, which they had iuſtly deſerued. The Angell vaniſhed; &amp; <hi>Efrem</hi> ſpeaking after with thoſe priſoners, found that to be true which the Angell had told him; and they were executed for offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which they had not commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and ſatisfied thus for others, which had been committed by them.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the iuſt iudgments of God, whereby he gouernes the world, and addreſſes his elect to the end of eternall happines, for which he choſe them. And from hence wee muſt learne, to thinke holily of God, in all thoſe tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and aduerſities, which he may ſend vs in this life: confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing<pb n="216" facs="tcp:15770:115"/>and acknowledging that he proceedes moſt iuſtly with vs; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe for our ſinnes wee deſerue thoſe puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which he ſends vs, yea and others which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably greater. And we muſt know &amp; confeſſe moreouer, that herein he ſhewes vs an vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able kinde of mercy; for as much as by the light, and ſhort puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this life, he not onely deliuers vs from thoſe fierce pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Purgatory, but alſo from the eternall torments of Hell.</p>
            <p>Thus did that holy <hi>Tobias</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the tribulations, which God ſent him; for he receiued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> willingly for his ſinnes; and ack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowledged that the puniſhment was very iuſt, &amp; that he deſerued both that, &amp; a farre greater. And he acknowledged that God ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him a ſoueraigne kind of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, for as much as he puniſhed<pb n="217" facs="tcp:15770:115"/>him that ſo he might deliuer him both from the faults, and from the penalties, alſo which he had incurred thereby; ſo to ſaue him in the e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. This doth he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe by ſaying thus, <hi>Tob.</hi> 3. Iuſt art thou, ô Lord, and all thy iudgments are very iuſt; for if we haue been deliuered into the hands of our enemies, to be made captiues and to be deſtroyed and killed by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to become the very ſcorne of all nations, it is becauſe we haue ſinned againſt thee, in not keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy comaundments, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſing with a pure hart in thy preſence. And further, confeſſing the great mercy wherewith God puniſhed them for their ſinnes, he ſaith, <hi>Tob.</hi> 13. Our Lord puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes vs for our ſinnes, and the ſame Lord ſhall ſaue vs for his mercies ſake. After this manner, by the knowledge of our ſinnes,<pb n="218" facs="tcp:15770:116"/>and of the puniſhment which we deſerue for the ſame, wee are to embrace all thoſe aduerſities which God may ſend vs in this life, with much
<hi>Patience,</hi> yea and wee muſt praiſe, and thanke him for them.</p>
            <p>Another, and a very efficacious meanes, whereby wee muſt helpe our ſelues to ſuffer all tribulation with <hi>Patience,</hi> is inſtantly to reſort to Almighty God in any affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ours, whether it be great or ſmall; beſeeching him, with our whole hearts, that he will giue vs ſtrength to beare it well; and to conforme our ſelues en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely to his moſt holy will. And although it be lawfull to deſire of God, that he will take the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation from vs, (ſo that yet wee ſtill reſigne our ſelues to his good pleaſure, that ſo he may doe that which ſhall moſt import<pb n="219" facs="tcp:15770:116"/>our ſaluation:) yet this is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; but our better ſuite is to be, that he will helpe vs to endure it, and ouercome it.</p>
            <p>When Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> with the leaue of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to walke vpon the water, <hi>Matt.</hi> 14. and when he found, that a ſtiffe winde was riſen, he grew troubled, and diſtruſtfull; and began to ſincke; and our Lord to deliuer him out of that great danger of drowing, did not cauſe the winde to ceaſe (as Saint <hi>Iohn Chryſoſtome</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues) but ſtretched forth his hand, and laid hold on him therewith; and made him walke vpon the water, till he brought him backe to the ſhip. Now this muſt wee beg of God in our troubles, nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that he will take vs by the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and that he will vouchſaffe vs his helpe and fauour; that ſo our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions may doe vs no hurt; but<pb n="220" facs="tcp:15770:117"/>that ſuffering them with <hi>Patience,</hi> they may yeeld great fruite to our ſoules, and be of much glory to Almighty God. This is that which <hi>Dauid Pſal</hi> 117. begged of God in his tribulations; and that which he deſired and begged, he alſo obtained, as himſelfe affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſaying. In my tribulation I called vpon my Lord and my God, and cryed out to him in the moſt internall part of my heart: and he, of his infinite mercy, heard my voice from that holy temple of his, which is heauen: and he accepted my prayer, and imparted that fauour which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe meanes, there is yet another, which is very effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, towards the obtaining of <hi>Patience,</hi> and it is to ponder pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly well, how all the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions and puniſhments which
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:15770:117"/>happen to vs in this life, be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by the prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, and are ſent vs by his holy hand, for our good. And (beſides thoſe other teſtimonies, whereby wee haue proued this truth elswhere)
<hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord declared it in his holy Ghoſpell ſaying thus.
<hi>Matt.</hi> 10. <hi>Feare not, for all the haires of your heads are numbred.</hi> The meaninge is, that God hath ſo particular care, and prouidence ouer you, that he hath counted euen all the haires of your heads, and knowes the number of them all; and there is nothing done, euen concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any of them, which he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daines not, for the good of that man, who puts his confidence in him. Now if Almighty God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the memory and care of ſo light and triuiall thinges, as are the haires of our head (which ſerue but for the ornament of<pb n="222" facs="tcp:15770:118"/>men, and which although they be cut off, doe not put the parties to any paine,) and this ſo fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e, as that euen one of them muſt not be cut, or loſt, without his pleaſure; how much more tender care will he take of the life, and ſaluation of that man, who puts his truſt in him; and of all thoſe principall thinges, which belong to him, that he may conſerue, and cheriſh, and ordaine them for the good of his ſoule; and not permit that he be put to the leaſt preiudice without his pleaſure; and that whatſoeuer happens to him, in order to his temporall affaires, may proue to the good and remedy of his ſoule; and for the doing all that which is fit for the carrying him on, to the end of eternall felicity, for which he was created.</p>
            <p>This is the nature of <hi>Patience,</hi>
               <pb n="223" facs="tcp:15770:118"/>whereof wee haue ſpoken; and theſe are the moſt excellent ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and frui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s thereof. Theſe are the meanes, whereby it is to be obtained, and theſe are the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, whereby wee haue been taught it by <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord. Let vs therfore procure to obtaine it, and moreouer to exerciſe it to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the whole world; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with that which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith thus to
<hi>Timothy: ep.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>Embrace, and exerciſe Patience dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly.</hi> And that alſo, which he ſaith to the <hi>Theſſal. ep.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>be patient, and ſuffer at the hands of all men.</hi> By this moſt pretious vertue of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> wee ſhall obtaine, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue all the gifts of God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuperiours to all our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. For <hi>Patience</hi> will fortify vs in the confeſſion of our Faith, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt tirants; giuing vs ſtrength to endure all their torments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi>
               <pb n="224" facs="tcp:15770:119"/>conſerues the ſupernaturall loue of God, and of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; for it giues vs courage to reſiſt all thoſe thinges which are contrary to charity. <hi>Patience</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues and giues perfection to wiſedome; taking away thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments of anger, and ſorrow, which obſcure the ſoule.
<hi>Patience</hi> builds vp abſtinence, and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; inabling a man to ſuffer hunger, and thirſt, and to bring ſenſual appetites into ſubiection. <hi>Patience</hi> defends iuſtice, encreaſes humility, conſerues peace, and purity of heart; and giues perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance in all vertue. And ſo it fulfilles that, whereof Saint <hi>Iames chap.</hi> 1. ſaith, <hi>that it makes the worke perfect;</hi> becauſe it giues perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and completenes to all the vertues.</p>
            <p>O bleſſed <hi>Patience;</hi> happy are they who poſſeſſe thee. For thou<pb n="225" facs="tcp:15770:119"/>art the vertue, which giueſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance in all good things; and which openeſt the way to heauen, where wee may ſee with perfect charity, &amp; delight with ſupreme loue, in that infinite beauty of God; and poſſeſſe for euer thoſe giftes of glory, which he hath prouided for them who continue in his ſeruice, according to that which our Lord promiſed ſaying; <hi>He who perſeuers to the end, shall be ſaued.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
